<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The vvhole summe of Christian religion, giuen forth by two seuerall methodes or formes the one higher, for the better learned, the other applyed to the capacitie of the common multitude, and meete for all: yet both of them such, as in some respect do knit them selues together in one. By Edmund Bunny Bacheler of Diuinitie.</title>
            <author>Bunny, Edmund, 1540-1619.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1576</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 203 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 88 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17244</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4096</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118853</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854060</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854060</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19467</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17244)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19467)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 412:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The vvhole summe of Christian religion, giuen forth by two seuerall methodes or formes the one higher, for the better learned, the other applyed to the capacitie of the common multitude, and meete for all: yet both of them such, as in some respect do knit them selues together in one. By Edmund Bunny Bacheler of Diuinitie.</title>
                  <author>Bunny, Edmund, 1540-1619.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 70, [2] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Thomas Purfoote, for Lucas Harison and George Bishop, dwelling in Paules Churchyarde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1576.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christianity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19467:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19467:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>¶ <hi>The vvhole Summe of Chriſtian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>giuen forth by two ſeuerall</hi> Methodes or Formes: the one higher, for</hi> the better learned, the other applyed to <hi>the capacitie of the common multitude,</hi> and meete for all: yet both of them ſuch, as in ſome reſpect do knit them ſelues together in one.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By EDMVND BVNNY Bacheler of Diuinitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>It is God that commaunded the light to ſhine out of darkenes. who alſo hath ſhined in our heartes, to giue forth the light of the knowledge of the glory of God, in the face of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>See thou (therfore) that thou haue a pattern of ſound doctrine: that thou maiſt alwayes be ready, to giue an anſwere to euery man, that aſketh thee a reaſon of the hope that is in thee.</p>
               <bibl>2. Cor. 4. a. 6. 2. Tim. 1. c. 13. 1. Pet. 3. c. 15.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>¶ <hi>Jmprinted at London by <hi>Thomas Purfoote, for Lucas Hariſon</hi> and George Biſhop, dwelling in Paules Churchyarde. 1576.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:19467:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19467:2"/>
            <head>¶ <hi>TO THE MOST Reuerende Father in God, his very good Lorde and</hi> Maſter, <hi>Edmunde,</hi> by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence of God Archbiſhop of Caunterbury, Primate of all England, and Metropolitane.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ince the tyme THAT IT HATH PLEA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the goodneſſe of God, that in our dayes Religion or the Faith of Chriſte ſhoulde be deliuered from the chaines of darkenes, and come forth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine with her wonted glorie, many of the learned &amp; godly diſpoſed haue done their endeuour, to make ſo plaine a way as they could, to bring the ſame to the knowledge of others. whoſe endeuour and godly purpoſe althoughe I gladly graunt to be ſuch, as is to be of all men not only receaued, but alſo with all due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull reuerence imbraced: yet for the truthes ſake muſte I needes adde thus
<pb facs="tcp:19467:3"/> much thervnto, that although diuers of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue done very well, yet none hath ſo abſolutely performed the ſame in all reſpectets; but that others alſo may thinke of helping it forwarde; &amp; put to their ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to do what they can. Not that hereby I charge any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with error in ſome points of their doctrine: but only that I finde not in then ſo good a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thode or maner of teaching, as on the behalfe of all beginners were generally of vs all to be vviſhed. And although I may ſeeme, in the iudgement of ſome, to make this complaint without any cauſe: yet haue I the warrant of myne owne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience, both that there is cauſe vrge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t inough; &amp; that the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaint ought rather to be made on the behalfe of the truth, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be ſuppreſſed in ſome pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate reſpect. Of this am I ſure, that ſo lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g as we tye our ſelues to the very ſteps or footings of others, neither can we vſe the fredome of our owne pace, neyther do we admit the benefit of a better way.</p>
            <p>Vpon which occaſion, as I haue bene a while ſince perſwaded, that I coulde not better beſtow my labour, to the vſe
<pb facs="tcp:19467:3"/> of thoſe that wold gladly haue a grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, then if I ſhould both contract &amp; interprete the inſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of M. Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine (who in my minde hath come ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt to his purpoſe: ſauing only that he is partly to long, but eſpecially to hard for a beginner); &amp; thervpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſet in hande with the worke, &amp; acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pliſhed the ſame ſo well as I coulde: ſo haue I ſince that time, vpon further aduice of that mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, me ſelfe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>triued the Summe of all religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (ſo far as it hath pleaſed God to proſper the ſame in my handes) much ſhorter, &amp; playner in my opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the other by any meanes might haue bene brought vnto, following the order that he hath left vs. and becauſe the methods or formes of compacting religion to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether that yet are forth, are not (as I take it) come to that perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that were to be wished: therfore haue I ſtreightly followed none that yet is extant; but coaſted ouer to the au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t high way, ſo nere as I could aeſteming religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious a thing, that no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beſtow his labor better, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by adorning it ſo much as he can; and by making it plaine vnto
<pb facs="tcp:19467:4"/> others: whether he ſhall doo it by the leuell of thoſe that haue written be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, or by ſome other way of his owne; ſo long as in ſubſtaunce he neuer ſwarueth from the auncient truth.</p>
            <p>The miſliking that I haue of thoſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Methodes that yet are geuen forth, is not ſo abſolute as ſome may take it: and, in effecte, is no more but this. Of Methodes we haue two principall ſorts. The firſt is the ſame vvhich goeth by the order of the Cathechiſme: the other, that which the learned do (for the moſt part) follow, in their Inſtitutions or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon places of Chriſtian religion. That kinde of Method that followeth the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Cathechiſme, doth in deede diſcloſe vnto all, after their maner, what is ment by the ten Commaundementes by the articles of the Fayth, and by the Lordes prayer: and by occaſion therof, doth alſo diſcourſe of all Religion, in ſuche ſorte as occaſion there is offered. But ſeeing that the matter of theſe doth very muche mingle together, the treatiſe that ſhal go by their leuell, muſt nedes come short of a perfect Method.
<pb facs="tcp:19467:4"/> Neuertheleſſe, they doo very well geeue foorth the true ſenſe of the chiefeſt points: and becauſe theſe three thinges before recited are in a maner the onely bookes of the common people, they are no doubt in that reſpect to ſingular vſe, for that they open thoſe thinges vnto them. That which the learned do com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly follow in their Inſtitutions and common places, doth come much nerer to the nature of a iuſt method; but yet doth not fully attaine thervnto, ſo farre as I am able to iudge: many of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſing but of particulars, not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently tyed together; and the others fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing ſo much the receiued order, that they alſo do not aptly ynough ſort eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre to his propre place. examples vvherof I could geue ynovv, but that ſo doing I might be tedious. my concluſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therfore shalbe this, that although both theſe ſorts are to very good purpoſe, &amp; doo very vvell diſcloſe vnto vs the very ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: yet for the Method or maner of deliuering the ſame; they haue yet ſo farre miſſed the marke that they shot at, that there is row me for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb facs="tcp:19467:5"/> to ſticke betwixt them &amp; the marke, who ſoeuer ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hit it. &amp; although it be an eaſier matter to find that there is winning, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſhed thoſe that are gone before: yet what should let, but that euery one may do his deuour, howſoeuer it shall fall out in the ende.</p>
            <p>As for me ſelf, although I know my skil &amp; iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to be but meane; yet me think I haue eſpied a couple of wayes, whereby religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> might be geuen forth ſome what more orderly the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yet it is. And becauſe it hath pleaſed god to bring the ſame to my knowledge, I thought it my duty to impart the ſame vnto others, not onely that I be not fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, to haue hidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my tale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: but alſo to thende, that ſuch as God shall better furnish, may put to their handes and helpe it forwarde.</p>
            <p>The former of thoſe is ſomwhat higher, &amp; ſuch as doth not eaſily come vnder the capacitie of the common ſort: for that throughout the whole diſcours, it doth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſet by ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; gathereth all, whatſoeuer is done, &amp; the glory thereof only to God. which kinde of teaching, though to vs it be harder, yet is it (in reſpect of the cauſe it ſelfe) a great deale more naturall, and
<pb facs="tcp:19467:5"/> hath his vvarrant in the vvorde of God.</p>
            <p>The other is of an eaſier kind, &amp; paſſeth after the ſame maner, that the holy ghoſt we ſee doth vſe, when he ſubmitteth his ſpeach vnto vs, &amp; applieth his talk to our capacitie: euer directing the talke vnto man, &amp; making him as it were an agent in all thoſe matters that belong thervn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. which kind of teaching the common ſort do accompt more meete for them.</p>
            <p>Howbeit in my mind it is much better to haue both together, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to haue either apart by it ſelfe. Firſt becauſe the nature of the cauſe is ſuch, as that either of them doth ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> giue a very good ſupply to the other: &amp; ech of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo linketh with other, that they cannot wel be parted a ſunder. Then alſo, becauſe al men are not always beginners, but many preſsing on to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther perfection. ſome coueting no more but to crepe below: others deſiring to get ſomwhat higher. ſome hauing ſo weake a ſight, that the ſunne beſt liketh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, when clouds intercept the brightnes therof: o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ging to haue thoſe clouds break, and to enioy al the whole brightnes, that the ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne is able to yeld the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. which two no
<pb facs="tcp:19467:6"/> doubt were the very cauſes, that the holy Ghoſt hath ſo tempered his ſpeach, that ech of theſe may euer haue whereon to feede.</p>
            <p>In which reſpect, thus much I haue to deſire of both, that eyther of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> taking what is their owne, or prepared for them, they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent them ſelues that others alſo may haue their portion. Thoſe that are ſtronger, and able to walke the harder way, may ſo beſtow the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues if they liſt. But yet in the midſte of their ſtrength, let them remember, that ſome others are vveake: and ſo not be greeued, that the vveake alſo haue to ſerue their turne. So on the other ſide, the vveake muſt know, that others are ſtrong. yf them ſelues may haue vvhat is meete for them, they may not repine, that others haue a leſſon beyonde them. Let euery one take his owne to him ſelfe: the reſt let him gladly leaue vnto others. Let God be good and gracious to all: let him prouide aſvvell for the one, as for the other, let him ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iourne on the earth, vvith thoſe that are not able yet to riſe higher: and let him take vp thoſe vvith him, whom his vviſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb facs="tcp:19467:6"/> hath framed meete therevnto.</p>
            <p>Theſe cauſes therefore mouing, I haue thought good to couple theſe two me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodes together, to ſet them abroade, and to preſent your Grace therevvith. and, if it pleaſe you, the one for your fare-well from the See of Yorke: the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I ſay not, ſo muche to the welcome vnto the other (let thoſe doo that, that haue gayned thereby) as that, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though your Grace be nowe remoued from vs of this your former prouince of Yorke, not only in perſon, but alſo from the peculiar charge therof: yet that your Grace vvould euer be ready (as vve no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing doubt but you wil) to doo vs good as occaſion ſhall ſerue. Hovv good opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities your Grace hath to do good vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to many, as others do very gladly behold them; ſo your ſelfe alſo may ſo farre vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folde them before your eyes, as beſt may encourage you euer to take the aduaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of them. Firſt hovv much God hath done for you, and vvhat good giftes he hath layde vp in you, to the vſe of his Churche heere with vs, it is a thing bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter knowne, then that it needeth any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porte
<pb facs="tcp:19467:7"/> of me. But this may I ſay, that her Maieſtie that occupieth the place of God next vnder him in theſe her dominions, hath not bene behinde in clothing with honour theſe good and commendable graces of God: aduauncing you to ſo high eſtate, that vſing the oportunitie therof, your Grace may doo very much good, not only wher your proper charge lyeth, but alſo throughout the vvhole Realme. The fauour of the people (gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally of the better ſorte) ſo embraceth the ſame, that whence your G. departure is made, thence do we heare co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>playnts of loſſe: whither the aduauntage is fallen, there do we ſee tokens of ioy, &amp; a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunce of a gayne obteined. Theſe are no ſmall helpes of dooing much good. when wiſdome &amp; zeale are both at home to order and gouerne all things aright; whom the authoritie and fauour of the Prince doth ſo vvell accompanie &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mende vnto others; to whom the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are ſo well affected, that they gladly like of, and imbrace his dooings: that man may doo much; and is well incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged, not to ſpare for any paynes to
<pb facs="tcp:19467:7"/> be doing good. and as on the one ſide it would be offenſiue to the iuſtice of god, and therevvithall prouoke ouer greuous a vengeaunce, to ouerſlip ſuche oportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, when as the Church ſo much doth neede, that they ſhould be taken: ſo on the otherſide, it is a thing ſo welcome vnto him, to ſee al his talents put to ſuch vſe, eſpecially when the caſe doth more ſpecially ſo require, that he crowneth the ſame with euerlaſting peace.</p>
            <p>God be thanked, that we haue the Goſpell among vs, ſo well as we haue it: and I pray God we may long enioy it. Neuertheleſſe, whoſoeuer examineth the matter more narrowly, me think, he may finde, that the Scepter of Chriſtes king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, is not ſo aduaunced among vs as vvere expedient: but rather in ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hinges cauſed to ſtoupe, and reſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed more, then is ſeemely for the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſtie of it. Religion vvith vs (I feare) may be in caſe of that plante, that for a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hile hauing harboured Ionas, was ſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t with ſo naughtie a worme, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat quickly it withered, &amp; left him again
<pb facs="tcp:19467:8"/> to the heate of the ſunne. Sure I am, that there is vvorke ynough to be done, to occupie all. Let thoſe therefore that ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> at the ſterne, take heede leaſt if novve vvhyle they dravve to the Rockes, they correct not their courſe, it be ere long to late for them to wiſh they had done it</p>
            <p>God continue and increaſe his grace towards you: geue you eyes, euer to ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> what is to be done; ſtrength, and rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dines, to performe the ſame: now to repayre the ruines of Zion, and at length to reſt in heauenly Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Graces most humble ſeruaunt in Christe</hi> Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munde Bunny.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:19467:8"/>
            <head>The Preface to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing already made de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of my purpoſe and meaning in ſetting forth theſe two Summes of Chriſtian Religion (as appeareth in the Preface that goeth before) I ſhal not neede; gentle Reader, to recite any part thereof agayne vnto thee. Neuertheleſſe ſome thinges there are, wherein it ſhall not be amiſe, to direct my penne a little to thee.</p>
            <p>Firſt of all therefore I nothing doubt, but that ſome there will be, that wil hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly like, that Religion ſhoulde be geuen forth after the maner of theſe two Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodes. Becauſe the former doth ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſely put by man for any agent in thoſe matters, and gathereth the whole glory of all onely to God: the other, lying within the bounds of the ten-Commaundemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, will ſeeme vnto them to be no more but only ſome parte, in no wiſe the whole by any good order. Thou therefore per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps
<pb facs="tcp:19467:9"/> wilt loke, that I ſhould ioyne here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto ſome defence of my dooing. and in deede I do not denie, but that, not onely the eyes of the common multitude do as yet remayne ſo dazeled, that they are not able to perceiue either of theſe very plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: but alſo, that certayne hoſtile mindes cannot in any wiſe be content to yeelde to the former of them, or, in theſe matters of ſpiritual glory, that they ſhuld haue none, and God ſhould haue all. Howbeit, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I will not be tedious to thee, I will holde of my hande from that kinde of la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and ſay no more but this only: that whenſoeuer it ſhall pleaſe God to open the eyes of the one, and to kill the cankre of pride in the harts of the other, then ſhal they alſo playnly perceyue, that they haue here no cauſe of miſliking. Tyl that time, we leeſe but our labour, if we looke that the blinde ſhould ſee; or that the proude ſhould freely geue all glory to God.</p>
            <p>An other thing, wherein I thought it ſomewhat needeful to content thy minde, is to preue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t a doubt, that otherwiſe might happily ariſe vnto thee. For I think thou wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> looke, that I ſhould haue furniſhed
<pb facs="tcp:19467:9"/> my Margent with ſo conuenient a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Scriptures, as were ſufficient to confirme the truth that is heere ſet down: as it is the maner of many to do. as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching which matter, thus much I ſay, that I do accompt ſuch dealing, then eſpecially to be needefull, when we deliuer ſuche poyntes of doctrine, as are hardly recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of euery one. For who ſeeketh profe in a matter that is apparant inough? Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therfore that in theſe two treatiſes I write no newe thing, but onely gather to an other Method ſuch things as others haue already ſufficiently proued; and are nowe (almoſt) of all men receyued, that haue a good will and loue to the trueth: I wote not, howe I might haue giuen an accompt vnto God, if eyther nowe I had beſtowed my time therein, when I haue other more needefull buſines; or ſhould haue kept in this that I haue done, vntill <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eyſure mighte haue ſerued to haue done the other. Neuertheleſſe my purpoſe is, if it ſhall pleaſe God to geue me ſtrength <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd oportunitie therevnto, and if none other ſhall well preuent me, not onely to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſtowe ſome vſuall number of quotatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s
<pb facs="tcp:19467:10"/> on it: but to geeue the attempt, to reduce the whole ſcriptures therevnto, &amp; the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of euery membre therof to ſome part of it. that ſo it may be a more profitable method to thoſe that ſhall ſtudie it more exactly. But as I am not able as yet to do it (eſpecially tyll I haue gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome other things out of mine ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds) becauſe I know the worke will grow to a great labour, &amp; require no ſmall quantity of time thervn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to: ſo I do not thinke it beſt in any other reſpect, to be ſo haſtie for that matter. that ſo I may win a further tyme of delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the methode it ſelfe. truſting that time, and the help of others, ſhall at le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth bring it to better perfection: and ſo make it meter to be furniſhed with quotations. In the meane ſeaſon, ſith now I haue not opportunitie to doe it as I woulde, or to mine owne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tentatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I can be very well content altogether to hold off my hands from it. yf any others to their priuate vſe ſhall in their reading, ſort the ſcriptures &amp; other good authors therevnto, on their behalfe, &amp; to their encouragement, thus much will I not ſticke to ſay, that, vnleſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I be farre deceiued, their paynes ſhal
<pb facs="tcp:19467:10"/> returne with ſo happy encreaſe, that ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her ſhall they euer repent them of it, nor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſily finde, howe they might otherwiſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aue beſtowed their labour to muche bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er purpoſe. And whenſoeuer a ſtudent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hal find any part of al ſcripture, or of any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ther good author, or any example or te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>timonie of others, that can not aptly be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>educed, to ſome parte of this method, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hen let him be ſure of one of theſe two, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat eyther the methode is vnperfect, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r els him ſelfe doth not vnderſtande <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t. whiche ſorting of the Scriptures <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hervnto, will alſo he a very good way to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erfect the method. For ſo ſone as we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ght on any place, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we can not perceaue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o come within the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſe of it, then fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing out where it ought to be, we may be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>olde to conclude, that in that place it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> vnperfect. But ſo farre as me ſelfe can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et ſee, I am not aduiſed of any parte of Scripture, that may not very aptly be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uced to ſome parte or other of this me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hod. Neither coulde I content me ſelfe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ith it, tyll I had brought it to that order.</p>
            <p>And therfore to ſpeake ſomething more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>irectly of the vſe of it, I truſt that the vſe
<pb facs="tcp:19467:11"/> therof may be double. wherof the firſt is vniuerſall, or comon to all that haue no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> yet atteined to ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t knowledge of the Chriſtian faith. And that is this; to geu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a generall ſight of all religion, &amp; to lay in them the foundation of it. For my hop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is, that whoſoeuer ſhall well digeſt theſe two little bookes (a thing we may ſee of no great labour) he, by the helpe thereof may be ſo well grounded in Chriſtian re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, that there cannot lightly be moued a point of any great importance, but that he ſhalbe able to goe to the truth thereof and to ſee the place whence it doth ariſe to the better confirmation of his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment therin: as alſo it ſhall eaſe a good part of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> paines in reading y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> otherwiſe would be found there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, whoſoeuer ſhall firſt be grounded in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole body of religion, eyther by theſe, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by any other to the like effecte. The other vſe hereof is more ſpeciall: but ſuche as is of good importaunce. It doth apperteine to all thoſe, that ſpecially ſhall geue them<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelues to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtudy of Diuinitie. For who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer ſhal ſo do, they ſhal finde it a thing very nedefull, not onely to haue a note<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>booke,
<pb facs="tcp:19467:11"/> whereinto they may gather the floure of their reading, and the titles ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of preſcribed vnto them: but alſo to haue thoſe titles ſo to be deuiſed &amp; diſpoſed, as may be apteſt to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehend the thing that they ſeeke. and therfore many haue labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to gratifie ſtudentes in this behalfe: &amp; in that reſpect haue deſerued very well of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. As touching which matter, I for my part do not ſee, how a ſtudent of Diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie might better furniſhe his note-booke with titles, then to ſet downe the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers hereof in order as they followe: doing the ſame with aduiſement in choyce, and lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing to euery one ſuch as a proportion of ſpace, as he ſhall geſſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> matter will nede. No matter of diffcultie (to ſpeake of) to ſuche as know what a note-booke mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth. And my truſt is, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there are not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny matters of importaunce, not only, not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the ſcriptures, but alſo, not in the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, or in other good writers, appertei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the ſubſtaunce of religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that may not aptly and naturally be referred to ſome ſuche title as is conteined in theſe two bookes.</p>
            <p>For the better accompliſhment of this
<pb facs="tcp:19467:12"/> matter, as alſo for the better prouocation of al others to ſearch out the ſenſe of theſe litle books, I haue annexed herevnto ſuch a demonſtratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therof &amp; ſo liuely a repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation to the eye of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> principal parts, &amp; of euery particular point co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teined therin, as I was able to deuiſe in ſo ſmal a rome, expreſſing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> former booke vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> forme of a tree roote; and the latter by a couple of other trees. The former haue I made the roote, for that it is by nature the very grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d worke of the other: as may appeare in the opening of the firſte commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement. In whiche Roote euery prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall Maſter-Roote doeth expreſſe the chiefe and principall partes of the whole diſcourſe: as alſo the leſſer doo betoken inferiour members, euen to the laſte and leaſte of all. And as for the Trees, my meaning is this. the one of them repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth ſuch thinges as are forbidden by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundements, &amp; therefore is called the tre of death: the other, ſuch things as they require, and therefore is called the tree of lyfe. The roote aforeſaide, diuerſly taken, is roote vnto both. For the ignoraunce of
<pb facs="tcp:19467:12"/> thoſe things y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it conteineth, is roote vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the tree of death: and the knowledge of them, the roote vnto the tree of lyfe. And therfore haue I ſomewhat bared y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rootes of both theſe trees: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> (ſo far as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſcourſe therof doth lead) euery one may ſee it to be the ſelfe ſame roote, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> before is deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed. This alſo I haue prouided both in the Roote, and in the trees, that there be neither mo, nor fewer diuiſions or braun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of any, then there are ſeuerall partes or me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers in the diſcourſes that belong thervnto: nor otherwiſe growing or iſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth, thou the diuiſions or me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers of theſe diſcourſes doo ariſe one vpon an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. As it ſhalbe an eaſy matter for thoſe to eſpie, that will conferre them and the booke together: ſo that euer they remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber to kepe this order, (which I haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually obſerued) to beginne at their lefte hande in all Diuiſions, and to go to the right.</p>
            <p>Which that they may the better finde out, I haue not only lefte my trees with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out eyther fruite or leaues (as in deede the tree of lyfe hath ſeldome any ſtore of fruite amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vs: &amp; then why ſhould not the tree
<pb facs="tcp:19467:13"/> of death be ſo much the rather ſpoyled of this?) that ſo the Braunches them ſelues may better appeare how many they are &amp; how they ariſe: but alſo haue added certen letters both to the Roote, and to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Trees to bring y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> demo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtration &amp; the bookes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. that ſo, not onely thoſe that will more diligently ſtudy religion, may ſoner eſpie what titles to chuſe: but all others alſo, that will but read theſe bookes with aduiſement, may better perceiue, what pointes religion geueth forth vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be conſidered. But herewithall muſt they know, that this demonſtration doth not extend to the Preface, concluſion, or mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall notes in eyther of the bookes: nor to thoſe things y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in the text are added to the ſecond, third, fourth, &amp; fifte co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> latter booke. Otherwiſe there is not (to my reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>braunce) any one me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre of eyther of theſe books, that hath not his proper demo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, either in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> roote, or in one of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Trees: and that in ſuch ſort, as I truſt will be welcome to the diligent reader, for the light y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it doth carie with it. As alſo I dare be bold to ſay thus muche, that if any of thoſe that loue imbrodering
<pb facs="tcp:19467:13"/> or nedle worke, ſhall thinke good to bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row their flowers or Braunches hence, ſure I am that the beſt of vs all may here haue inow, to put in napkins to wipe our noſes.</p>
            <p>As for the ſonges that are ſet herevnto, they doe ſo reſemble y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matter it ſelfe, that euery one may ſee my meaning therein. The former of them is made vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſong of the Angell that brought y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhepheardes word of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> birth of Chriſte, geuing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glory of that our rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> only to God: a thing that cometh very neere to the argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the former booke. The other goeth vpon the ſenſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ten-co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dements, &amp; doth more preciſely comprehend the effect of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole latter booke: teaching the way that we ſhould walke. Seing therfore y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes we are naturally bent to refreſhe our ſelues with ſong, &amp; ſome, not onely are deſirous to ſing by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, but alſo couet to haue others to ſing with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and therwithall to haue ſuch recreation as the harmonie of muſicke can bring therevnto (which is veri much to moſt me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s nature) whereas before I had a note of a freind of mine in foure parts, which well agreth
<pb facs="tcp:19467:14"/> to this kind of making, and is not vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of the author of it, I thought it good to ſet all thoſe partes downe to the one, and to procure the like for the other: that, if ſo it ſhall pleaſe thee, thou alſo mayſt haue the vſe of them. and if thy hart ſhall goe with thy ſong, then dare I promiſe thee, that god him ſelfe ſhall like thy melodie.</p>
            <p>Theſe (gentle Reader) are the things that I had to imparte vnto ther. Theſe if thou take with the bookes them ſelues, thou haſt therwithall my whole meaning. Of what accompt it ſhal be with ſome others, as yet I knowe not, ſo alſo I care not. But who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer ſhal geue foorth better, I ſhal be as glad to receiue that, as I was readie in the ſame reſpect to publiſhe this. God geue vs al grace, to be thankful to him for this great light, that it hath pleaſed him to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde, to ſhine out of darknes in theſe our dayes: and while we haue it, to walke as becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the children of light. The night (mee thinketh) approcheth neare, then ſhall we hardly be able to walke. Time muſt be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, when time is offred. for time will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. And ſo in the Lord I bid thee hartily well to fare. this 20 of Aprill. 1576.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:19467:14"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19467:15"/>
            <head>Certayne other aduertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes to the Reader, of ſome notes to be ſet downe, and ſome faltes and poyntes to be amended, before that he reade the booke it ſelfe, ſo to make him to vnderſtand it the better.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>In the first booke.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>Fol. 1. b. lin. 4. put out, by. 2. a. in the title where as it is Sonne, it ſhoulde bee Father.</item>
                  <item>2. b. li. 21. for Thirdly, that he is &amp;c. ſay, Thirdly, that in the Godhead, &amp;c. as it followeth: and ſo ſtrike out thoſe 3 lines betwixt.</item>
                  <item>3. a. li. 14. for Fiftly, that &amp;c. ſay Fourthly, and laſt of all, that. &amp;c.</item>
                  <item>line 21. ſtrike out Sixtely and all that followeth to alteration, foure lines in al.</item>
                  <item>fol. 8. a. lin. 22. make a full poynt at him.</item>
                  <item>10. a. li. 14. for his, put in Gods.</item>
                  <item>10. b. lin. 17. for the, put in theſe.</item>
                  <item>lin. 21. put this poynt, at murther, and remoue that part of the parentheſis, to life in rhe next line.</item>
                  <item>11. a. li. 5. and 6. thus point it, to god, he &amp;c ſinne: yet &amp;c</item>
                  <item>15. a. 15. poynt it thus, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption;</item>
                  <item>15. b. poynt it thus, li. 9. Iewes,</item>
                  <item>lin. 11. eſtimation: lin. 13. inſuing:</item>
                  <item>Fo. 16. a. for world, point it worlde:</item>
                  <item>17. a. in the title for the holy Ghoſt put y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sonne: for 19, put 17.</item>
                  <item>18. a. for fo. 20. put fo. 18. li. laſt, for them. put them:</item>
                  <item>18. b. lin 21. put our after touching.</item>
                  <item>19. a for 17. put 19. and in the margent agaynſt the ſixte line, thou muſt put a note, that that treatice which laſteth till thend of the thirde page, compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole diſcourſe of the ſconde booke.</item>
                  <item>19. b. li, 1, for of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sonne, put of God the father, the Sonne,</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19467:15"/>
                  <item>lin 11. for man on the. &amp;c. put, man, &amp; all other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in heauen, earth, and hell on the one ſide; and al fantaſies of oure owne brayne on the other &amp;c.</item>
                  <item>20. a. for 18. put 20.</item>
                  <item>21. a. lin. 12. put, worketh it in them.</item>
                  <item>lin 18. for inwarde: put inwarde;</item>
                  <item>22 b in the margent for caſes put cauſes.</item>
                  <item>24 b lin 8. put, of yll; lin. 12. nothing;</item>
                  <item>25. a. put them (when</item>
                  <item>26 a lin. 21. you may put this note in the margent. Fol 19 a b 20 a. But af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwarde more largely in the ſeconde booke, in the Tree of lyfe. b. agaynſt the fourth line you maye ſet this note in the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent: Which alſo are more largely ſet foorth in the next booke in the Tree of Death.</item>
                  <item>lin. 15. for put by man &amp;c. ſay, put by eyther the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of God, or ſo much as their own fancies, that ſo &amp;c.</item>
                  <item>27 a. lin 2, for ſelues or other, put ſelues, or others</item>
                  <item>b. lin. 20. for ſetting, put ſetling.</item>
                  <item>29. for 31. put 29.</item>
                  <item>b. The text of Scripture apperteineth not to that only place, but to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole booke, and ſhoulde haue bene ſet laſt of all.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>In the ſecond booke.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>30. after the text of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, in ſuche bookes as bookes as haue not the place quoted, put in Eccle. 13. d. 12. 13.</item>
                  <item>31. for 29 put 31.</item>
                  <item>b lin 21, for Region, put Religion.</item>
                  <item>33 lin 9, for ſelues; poynt it ſelues.</item>
                  <item>b lin 7, ſpring:</item>
                  <item>34 a lin 10, at It req. beginne a new ſection.</item>
                  <item>20. Saintes:</item>
                  <item>21, ſelues,</item>
                  <item>34 b, in the title, The fyrſte Commaundemente. Which falt thou muſte a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mende once more in that commaun. and twiſe in the ſeconde.</item>
                  <item>35, b, lin, 1, for mankinde on &amp;c. put in, mankind, and all other creatures on the one ſide; and all conceites of our owne, on the other, We geue &amp;c.</item>
                  <item>In the margente reade, mankinde and all other
<pb facs="tcp:19467:16"/> creatures on the one ſide, that others, &amp;c.</item>
                  <item>39 b lin 6, for lawe, put lawe;</item>
                  <item>40 a li 8 for as put and. blaſt line, for Eerciſes put Exerciſes.</item>
                  <item>43 b, in the 12 line of the note put ſenſe.</item>
                  <item>44 b, lin 6, put out in.</item>
                  <item>46 b in the note lin. 24. reade thus, nor to them neither,</item>
                  <item>47 b. lin 2. done:</item>
                  <item>49 a lin. for. put: lin, 15, theſe. lin 16 this, lin, 23, for ben, put bent.</item>
                  <item>51, b, for reſt. put reſt;</item>
                  <item>52, a, lin, 15, for, put.</item>
                  <item>53, b, in the margent, lin, 29, for both in &amp;c, put in, the Braunches of both the Trees that bet. &amp;c.</item>
                  <item>55, a, li, 4, for; put: li, 5, for the ſeconde; put:</item>
                  <item>56, a, lin, 20, for: put.</item>
                  <item>62, b, lin, 24, for L put l.</item>
                  <item>64, b, in the title for ſixt put ſeuenth.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:19467:16"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A SHORT SVMME of Chriſtian Religion</hi> vnder the conſideration of the three perſons in the Trinitie, the <hi>Father, the Sonne, and the holy Ghoſt.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>Iſa.</hi> 44. <hi>d.</hi> 24. <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. <hi>c.</hi> 19.</p>
            <p>I the Lorde doo all thinges mee ſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone. Goe ye therefore, and teache all Nations, baptizyng them in the name of the Father, and of the Sonne, and of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:19467:17"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19467:17"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A short Summe of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion, vnder the conſideration</hi> of the three perſons in the Trinitie, the Father, the Sonne, and the holy Ghost.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S it is verye</hi> true that God onely is the Lorde, and the only doer or worker of al: ſo may y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole body of Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion be geuen forth in ſuche a methode or forme, as that the whole glory of all may well be gathered only to him. In ſo muche that as there are three diſtinct Perſons in the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head; ſo likewiſe may the effect or ſumme of all Religion be diſtributed into three ſuch principall partes, as may very fitly bee ſorted to euery of them: and ſo, the whole glory of all, left only to God. And thoſe principall parres of Religion which we meane to attribute, one to the Father, an other to the Sonne, the thirde vnto the holy Ghoſt, are; Firſt the ſecrete pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of God; or, what he ſhould meane in
<pb facs="tcp:19467:18"/> ordering this world and all things there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, in ſuch ſorte as he hath: ſecondarily the bringing forth of that his purpoſe, or the manifeſtation of it: thirdly by the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the ſame in others; directing, or framing all thinges to the due accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment therof.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Perſon of the Father.</head>
               <p>VNto the Perſon of the Father I at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute the ſecrete counſaile, or intent, or purpoſe of the Godhead, as touching his ordering this worlde and all thinges therein, in ſuch ſort as it hath pleaſed him to ordeine them. Which purpoſe of his was (as the ſequele therof, and many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of ſcripture declare) to make knowne, not man, or other creatures; but only him ſelfe. As touching which knowledge, or making of him ſelfe knowne, there are threee principall thinges to be conſidered. Firſt, what maner of knowledge of him it is, that he would geue forth of him ſelf.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:19467:18"/> Secondarily, in whome he woulde be knowne. Thirdly, and laſt of all, by what degrees he woulde haue this knowledge of him to be in man.</p>
               <p>As touching the firſte and principall of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heſe three, we haue to conſider that it is not that abſolute, or moſt full and perfect knowledge of him, which can be in none <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut onely in him ſelfe: but a certaine me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iocritie, or ſuche as might come vnder <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur capacitie. For that he ment not to geue forth that abſolute knowledge of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>im in the workemanſhip of this world, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t may ſufficiently appeare, for that, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her is the workemanſhippe of this world a ſufficient demonſtratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of it: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her are we of that creation or nature, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat we are able ſo muche as to conceaue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t. That I deny the workemanſhippe of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>his world to be a ſufficient demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion of it, the reaſon is this; becauſe it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f ſo ſmall continuaunce, that it can not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>herin expreſſe the eternitie of the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ead: and of ſo ſmall compaſſe, that it can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot therin expreſſe his Vbiquitie, or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eaſurablenes.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19467:19"/>
               <p>That I deny vs to be of that capacity tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> we are able to conceiue it, the reaſon is, becauſe we can in no wiſe be able cythe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in the ſhortnes of our dayes to meaſure his eternitie; or in the narrownes of our vnderſtanding, to comprehende him tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is Infinite.</p>
               <p>The mediocritie of this knowledge tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> I ſpeake of, or ſuch as may come vnde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> our capacitie, may for a further playnenes ſake, be diſtributed into theſe three parts the firſt of ſuch thinges as moſt properly concerne the perſon of the Godhead. th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſeconde of certayne other excellencies which are ſomewhat further of from the ſubſtaunce of his perſon. the thirde o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſuche thinges as concerne his will and pleaſure.</p>
               <p>Of the firſt ſort are theſe, Firſt that there is a God. Secondarily, that there is no other but He alone. Thirdly, that he is not of any ſet compaſſe, bodely ſhape, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> earthly nature: but Infinite, Spirituall, and Inuiſible. Fourthly, that in the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head there bee three diſtincte Perſons. wherof the firſt is of the Father: vnder which we conſider the Godhead as he is
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:19467:19"/> in his owne nature, not yet beeing made manifeſt, or declaring him ſelfe. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde of the Sonne: vnder whiche Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon we conſider the ſelfe ſame Godhead made manifeſt, or opening him ſelfe to be knowen of others; who therfore is called the Speache, the Image, and the Sonne of the Father. The thirde of the holy Ghoſt: vnder whiche we conſider the ſelfe ſame God, but working in others, that the Father may be knowen in hys Sonne, or (whiche is the ſame) that the Godheade may be ſeene in his Image. Fiftely, that theſe three Perſons are but one, and the ſelfe ſame God: for that there is none that can expreſſe the Godhead, or bring to paſſe that he be knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in others (which are the properties of the Sonne, and the holy Ghoſt) but onely God, and the ſelfeſame which in other reſpect is the Father. Sixthly, or laſt of all, that the Godhead is Eternal or Euerlaſting: that is, hath euer bene without beginning; can neuer haue any ending; neither yet any chaunge, or alteration.</p>
               <p>Of the ſeconde ſorte, that is, of thoſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther excellencies, that are euer ſomewhat
<pb facs="tcp:19467:20"/> farther of from the ſubſtaunce of his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and yet can neuer be ſeperated from the Godhead, are very many: but yet are ſuche, as may very well come vnder one cheefe and generall title; which is of his moſt excellent maieſtie, or incomparable glorie. and this ineſtimable glorie of his appeareth two maner of wayes. Firſte, becauſe him ſelfe is incomprehenſible: then becauſe he is of vnſpeakable good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. Incomprehenſible he is found to be, for that he is, not of bodily ſhape, earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly nature, or ſet compaſſe; but inuiſible, ſpirituall, and infinite. Good alſo he is two maner of wayes. firſte in him ſelfe: then towardes others. In the former re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecte he is ſounde to be good, for that he is full of all perfection: moſt holy, moſte mightie, moſt riche, and euer-laſting. His holineſſe is ſuche, as that neither is there<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in him ſelfe any ſteyne, or poſſibilitie to fall thereinto: neither can he lyke of any ſinne in others; neither in the worſe, not in the better. As touching his power, there be two thinges to be conſidered. howe greate or large it is: and, what are the braunches thereof. The largeneſſe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:19467:20"/> of his power appeareth in theſe foure poyntes. that he made, mayneteyneth, and guydeth, what ſo euer creatures there are in heauen, on earth, or in hell: hath all thinges euer before hys eyes, whether paſte, preſent, or yet to come; whether open, or hidde: hath all powers ſubiecte vnto him, in heauen, earth, and hell: and him ſelfe is almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, or, ſo fully able to doe what ſoeuer ſtandeth with his good pleaſure, that worthely he may be termed (as in deede he is, and none but he) the onely Lorde, or Maſter of all. The braun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of his power, are theſe two. his vnſearcheable wiſedome in diuiſing, and ordering of all thinges: and his inuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible ſtrength in bringing to paſſe, that euery thinge falleth out, as his wyſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome before ordeyned. His Riches or treaſures are moſt ineſtimable, for that him ſelfe alone hath all good thinges in his owne handes: whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Bodily, or Ghoſtly; momen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, or eternall. Eternall or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer-laſtinge needes muſte hee be: for that hee neuer hadde anye Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning;
<pb facs="tcp:19467:21"/> neuer can haue any ending; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yet is ſubiect to any chaunge, or al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration. As touching his goodnes in the other reſpect, that is, as it iſſueth foorth towards others, there be two principall braunches thereof: his iuſtice, and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. Vnto his iuſtice it doth apperteyne, that he is Ielous on his owne behalfe: &amp; Righteous towards others, that is, true in his ſayings; vpright in his iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts; in his vengeaunce ſeuere with co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient moderation. Vnto his mercy doo apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne theſe three: his patience or ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, when the offence is eyther great, or els deſerueth ſpeedy vengeaunce; his free pardoning; and all other his fauourable dealing. His fauourable dealing ſtret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth to all, but by diuers degrees: very much to all inferior creatures; much more to all mankinde; but moſt of al to his cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen people.</p>
               <p>Of the thirde and laſte ſorte are ſuche thinges as apperteine to his will or plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. which will of his hath a double con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration. Firſt, what it is in it ſelfe? which is for the moſt part vnknowen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs: but yet is the rule of abſolute equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19467:21"/> Then what it is towards others, that he woulde ordeyne to guide according therevnto. whiche alſo is declared to vs two maner of wayes. Firſt Summarily, or briefly: then more at large, or more particularly. Summarily his will is ſet foorth vnto vs in the Ten-Commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, and in other abridgementes, or ſhort ſummes. Whiche kinde of teaching he ſometimes vſeth, both that it may the better appeare what is the effect of parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars; and better remayne in freſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce. More at large he inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vs in the ſame, throughout all the Scripture beſides: and that to this ende, that we may the better vnderſtande thoſe ſhort ſummes; and knowe howe muche matter there is in them, if they be rightly vnderſtoode.</p>
               <p>As touching the ſecond, that is, in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he would be knowne, we haue to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that this glorious knowledge of him can neuer go out of him ſelfe, vntill he haue made wherein it ſhall ſhine; and him ſelfe caſt thither, or therevpon, or therein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to rather the beames of his glory. And we finde that his purpoſe was to haue two
<pb facs="tcp:19467:22"/> ſortes of creatures, in whom this know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege of him ſhould be. Some there ſhould be, that ſhould haue it but printed on the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: and ſo ſhould be in ſteede of bookes vnto others. as all other creatures are beſides man: whether they be Celeſtial; Terre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrial; or Infernall. Others there ſhould be, that ſhould not only haue this know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge imprinted on them: but alſo ſhould haue the ſame in ſuche ſorte inueſted or grounded within them, that they ſhould haue power, both in them ſelues, and in others, to beholde the Godhead. Of this ſort (keping within the bounds of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip of this world) we find<note n="*" place="margin">As for Angels and Diuels, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though we know, that thoſe alſo are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of god &amp; perceyue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> in thoſe god would haue a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayn know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lege of him: yet we doo not finde them to apperteyne to the workemanſhippe of thys worlde. So are they to vs, but parte of thoſe our afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayde bookes.</note> none but mankinde alone. But as he would haue this knowlege in man, ſo it is therwithal to be knowne, that in ſome (to whome it ſhould be to leſſe vſe, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we terme Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probates) he would haue it but in very vnperfect, and confuſed maner: in others (the choſen I meane, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhould reape ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by euerlaſting bleſſednes) he would haue it more ſoundly, &amp; in greater perfection.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:19467:22"/>
               <p>Concerning the thirde and laſt, that is, by what degrees his purpoſe was to haue it in thoſe that ſhoulde haue this knowledge in them after the ſounder and perfecter maner, we finde his purpoſe to haue bene, that in this world they ſhould haue it more darkely; and yet in great certaintie without doubting, and euer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing to a clearer light: in the worlde to come they ſhoulde haue it more clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; and in as greate perfection and glorie, as poſſibly maye bee in ſuche a Creature.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Perſon of the Sonne.</head>
               <p>VNto the Perſon of the Sonne we at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute, the bringing forth of this his purpoſe, out of the boſome or ſecrete counſell of the Father; or, in what ſorte it is made manyfeſt. as touching whiche we haue more ſpecially to conſider theſe two thinges: firſt, what is that worke wherein he hath made him ſelfe knowne: then, what are the principall partes thereof.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19467:23"/>
               <p>Concerning the former of theſe two, it is to be knowen, that we haue to caſt our eyes but to the workmanſhippe of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde, and of all other Creatures that are ordeyned to the vſe of man. For though it ſhould be ſo, that he had many other worl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des beſides this of ours, and many other workes as fayre, and fayrer then this: yet this onely, and none other is ordeyned to vs, wherein he will be knowen vnto vs.</p>
               <p>Concerning the other, that is, to finde out what are the principall partes of this manifeſtation of him ſelfe, this is a large and a worthy matter. And the parts ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of are theſe three; the beginning: the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing: and the finiſhing of it.</p>
               <p>That we may the better ſee in what ſort it was begunne, there are foure prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall things to be conſidered. Firſt, howe he made the world and all things therein, before that euer he made man. Seconda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, in what ſorte he made man. Thirdly, howe he delt with him, after that he had ſo made him. Laſt of all, howe God ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing finiſhed all that his worke, reſted the Seuenth day, and hallowed it.</p>
               <p>The firſt of theſe is, not only an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:19467:23"/> of his Prouidende, prouiding for vs before that we were: but alſo, an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his goodnes, preuenting vs; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thereby we perceyue he loued vs, before that euer we could deſerue any iote of his kindnes.</p>
               <p>The ſeconde leadeth vs to conſider, what kinde of one he made vs, firſte in Body; then in Soule. As touching our Body or earthly nature, he made man of an homely peece of earth. Which is, a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient proofe of Gods power: a preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatiue agaynſt pride that mighte ariſe when he ſhould beholde the excellencies wherwithall ſhortly after he ſhould be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dewed: and a figure of the excellent worke of Redemption, that afterwarde ſhoulde be rayſed, out of the baſe eſtate of the fleſh, or manhood of Chriſte. The woman he made of a ribbe taken out of Adams ſide beeing caſt aſleepe. Whiche is, a ſingular prepratiue truely to loue: and a figure of the Churche of God, whiche is, and can be none other, but only it, which is ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed out of the paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our Adam, Chriſt. As touching our Soule, he endewed both the man and the woman with notable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies
<pb facs="tcp:19467:24"/> (ſo to make them a more liuely image of him ſelfe) as may appeare by theſe fowre things. Firſt, that he made it to endure for euer. Secondarily, that he furniſhed it with a notable lighte of knowledge, not onely in theſe inferior matters of the world, both naturall and ciuill: but alſo with whatſoeuer apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teineth to the true worſhip of God, or to his ſpirituall kingdome. Thirdly, that he made him clene without any ſteine of ſinne; and fully able to fulfill the Lawe that afterwarde was geuen, or, to follow the rule of perfect righteouſnes; in deede, worde, and thoughte. Laſt of all, that he lefte him in ſo perfecte freedome of his wyll, that both he mighte ſtill haue done good, till of his owne accorde he had turned aſide: and yet, that when as it ſhould come to paſſe, that needes he would, he ſhould both leaue the way of righteouſnes and peace; and fall away to all iniquitie, and to a moſte wretched e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate. ſo, both to keepe him ſelfe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſteine, when man ſhoul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fall: and to make a way to the declaration of his Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and mercy.</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:19467:24"/>
               <p>The thirde, that is, the conſideration howe he dealt with man after that hee had made him ſo excellent a creature, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth in two principall poyntes. firſte, howe he dooth before prepare him to bring foorth the force of thoſe his excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies to the keeping of his Commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, when it ſhould be giuen: then, howe he geueth the commaundement it ſelfe. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the former of theſe, there are three poyntes that belong therevnto. For firſt he gaue him the vſe and ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raintie of all other creatures, that hee might the rather, neuer turne aſide his obedience or ſeruice to them: and haue therewithall bothe to prouoke hym to the ſeruice of God; and alſo to mainteyne him therein. Secondarily he gaue him to vnderſtande, that he was a moſt bleſſed creature, both by the place wherein he ſet him, that pleaſaunt Paradiſe; and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, by the Tree of life that he left him, which Tree of lyfe was left vnto him to feede on, as a Sacrament of his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed eſtate: and that, in the midſte of the Garden, euer to be before his eyes. Out of both which, man might haue gathered,
<pb facs="tcp:19467:25"/> that he was marueilous much beholding to God: and that, althoughe nowe he ſtoode, yet in proceſſe of time he mighte fall. Laſt of all, he fenſed him about with the exerciſe of bodely labour; geuing him charge to keepe and dreſſe the garden. out of which alſo he might haue gathered, not only that labour was a needefull exerciſe for him: but alſo that he had neede to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue him ſelfe in the eſtate that God had giuen him. As touching the latter of them, that is, the geuing of the Commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement it ſelfe, we haue to conſider three thinges. Firſte, what the Commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment it ſelfe was: that is, to forbeare one tree, that it pleaſed God to exempte. which was but obedience: and that, but in a ſmall matter. Then how he directeth him to keepe it. whiche he doth, both by denouncing vnto him moſt certayne, and extreme wretchednes, when ſoeuer he ſhould breake it: and therewithall inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preting the name vnto him, that other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe might haue bene very daungerous. Laſt of all, ſeeing that there is no ſeruice of God, till a commaundement be giuen; and as yet this commaundement was
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19467:25"/> not geuen till this preſent, that here is an other argument, that the goodneſſe of God euer preuenteth our deſertes.</p>
               <p>The fourth and laſt, which is, how he reſted the ſeuenth day, may firſt of all be a figure of our reſt in Chriſt: in this world begunne; finiſhed in the worlde to come. Secondarily, it is an argument or pledge, that we are ſanctified, not by our ſelues, or by any other: but only by the Lord him ſelfe. Thirdly, it ought to be an example vnto vs to do the like: ſo to take tyme; to the conſideration of Gods workes; and to other godly meditations. Laſt of al, it may be, that God therby would ſignifie, that he did then holde off his hands; and gaue roome and leaue to the Temptor.</p>
               <p>Hauing ſeene howe it pleaſed God to beginne, nowe haue we to ſeeke oute, howe he went forwarde with the ſame, or the continuaunce and proceſſe of the matter, or of this worke ſo begunne. In whiche there be two principall pointes to be conſidered. firſte in what ſort he brought to paſſe, that man fell away from his innocencie, and happie eſtate. then in what ſorte he brought in the worke of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption,
<pb facs="tcp:19467:26"/> or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> remedie ordeyned before.</p>
               <p>In the former of theſe, there are fyue ſpeciall poyntes to be conſidered. Fyrſte, what the eſtate of mankind became there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by. as touching which, we haue to know, that firſt concerning his Soule the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall parte of him, his naturall gyftes were not cleane loſte: but very much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayed. as for his other excellencies which we may terme Supernaturall, firſte his Immortalitie was pouldred with eternal tormentes. and as for the reſt, firſte them ſelues were ſo cleane loſte, that for thoſe pointes there remayned in mans nature no goodnes at all. then alſo in place of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he had, for pefect knowledge, ſtarke blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and error: for abilitie to fulfill y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law, not ſo much power left, as to thinke one good thought, but was fully repleniſhed with all iniquitie: for freedome of will, moſt miſerable bondage of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the power of Sathan wholly aduaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced. Then alſo to come to the body, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came moſt miſerable. partly in this world, both in it ſelfe, by diſfigurings, diſtempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rature, diſeaſes, griefes, &amp; naturall death; and by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> curſe that was caſt on other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:19467:26"/> that were for the vſe of man: but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially in the world to come, being ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect then to euerlaſting wretchednes. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condarily, that this wretched eſtate was from our firſt parents deriued to all their poſteritie: and three reaſons may be ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen therefore. Firſt, becauſe they ſtood for vs all, to haue and to loſe, for vs or from vs, what ſoeuer was beſtowed on them. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, becauſe the ſinne was ſo great, that it could not be ſufficiently puniſhed, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it were caſt on their poſteritie alſo: eſpecially, yf we caſt our eyes to the abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute perfection of his holines and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes. The thirde and laſte, becauſe we haue experience, that the ſaide corruption is inueſted in vs. Thirdly, whether God were the worker of this their ouerthrow or not. Concerning whiche it is to be knowne, firſt, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he did it: and that it muſt nedes ſo be, for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there is no other agent, or working powre in all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, but his alone. then, that he did it not immediately by him ſelfe: but by his executioner the diuell; and the readie inclination of man him ſelf. Fourthly, to what ende he ſhould do it. which was, to worke forth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> purpoſe
<pb facs="tcp:19467:27"/> of the Father; to ſhewe forth eſpecially, both his iuſt vengeaunce on thoſe, whom he woulde not vouchſafe to raiſe vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine: and his mercie on thoſe, whome he would recouer. The fift and laſte is, to ſearch out, how this worke may be attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to God, and yet he not made there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the author of ſinne. Concerning which it is to be knowne, firſt of all, that all the workes of God are ſo righteous, &amp; him ſelfe ſo well able to anſwere for him ſelfe, that neither ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he do any yll; neither doth he neede our defence. Then alſo, that whereas in all things that are done, there is a double conſideration, one of the dede it ſelfe; the other of the qualitie, or forme, or maner of it: to diſtinguiſhe betwixt the two, bringeth a ſufficient light to the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. ſo that euer we attribute the deede it ſelfe, without any exception, to God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone (as in murther) the bereeuing a man of his life: the qualitie, yf it be good (as the lawfull putting a man to death for his deſertes) to God alſo; yf it be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different (as in naturall death) to the courſe of nature whiche God hathe ſet: which notwithſtanding euer is at
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:19467:27"/> the becke of God. Yf the qualitie be yll (as vnlawfully to take a mans lyfe from him) and ſo might ſeeme to ſtreyne the deede ſo farre, that yf the deede ſhould be adſcribed to God: he alſo ſhoulde be the author of ſinne, yet are theſe two thinges therewithall to be knowne. Firſt, that as it is the worke of God, he euer hath ſome other qualitie or forme apperteyning therevnto that is good. Then alſo, that the yll qualitie or forme of the yll deed, is not eyther eternall with God (becauſe the diuill him ſelfe the author of it, was him ſelfe the creature of God) or to him deriued from God at his creation (for that the goodnes of God is ſuch, as that no yll can proceede of it: no more then darknes can come of light; of health, ſicknes; of life, death, &amp;c.): But of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell as of his owne, afterwarde obtey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned becauſe he did not abide in the truth. Sinne beeing by nature but the decay of righteouſnes: as darkenes is, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> want of light; ſicknes no more but the want of health; and death no more but wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of life. So that Sinne might very well firſte be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne in him, when firſt he fell.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19467:28"/>
               <p>In the latter, that is, in the bringing in of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> remedy y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was before ordeined, there are three things to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidered. firſt, how he prepared mankind to receaue it before that fully he brought it in. then, howe he brought forth the worke it ſelfe. thirdly, howe he hath euer ſince mainteined and aduaunced the ſame.</p>
               <p>To beginne with the firſt of theſe three, we find y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he did it diuerſly: ſomewhat o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt age of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, then in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſecond. In the firſt age of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world (till the calling of Abraham) he did altogether (to ſpeake of) eſtraunge him ſelfe to the world: and yet therewithall gaue notable tokens of a reconciliation made in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret purpoſe of God, and that the worke therof ſhould be accompliſhed when time ſhould come. as touching y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eſtraunginge of him ſelfe, we haue to conſider in what maner it was: and to what ende it was done. The maner of it appeareth in theſe three poynts. Firſt, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he droue out of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe our firſt au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceſtors, immediately af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fall; and fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the fruition of the Tree of life. Secondarily, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> afterward he choſe vnto him no one people or nation in all
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:19467:28"/> the world: but onely a few particular men of diuers families. Laſt of all, that vnto thoſe particulars alſo he did not geue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſet forme of religion, or manifeſtation of his will: but onely delte with them by the law written in their hartes; and by extraordinary reuelation. The ende, or cauſe wherefore it was donne, was to teache them howe odious they were in the moſte holy iudgementes of God. both to dryue them from that naturall here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie of man, to haue ſome good opinion of their owne righteouſnes: and to prouoke them to ſeeke for helpe by the way of mercie. As touching the tokens of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation that I ſpake of, we haue in lyke maner to ſee, what they were: and why hee did vouchſafe to geue them. Of thoſe tokens there were two ſortes. ſome that inſued immediately after the fall: and ſome that were founde in the proceſſe of tyme that followed. Immediately after the fall, he came to rayſe them vp againe: ſought them out where they were hid: put them in minde of the cauſe of their miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: curſed the ſerpent for their ſakes: pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed them a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>queſt ouer him: caſt vpon
<pb facs="tcp:19467:29"/> them but a ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tle diſcipline, although their ſinne were maruelous great: and made them garmentes to couer their nakednes. In the proceſſe of time that followed in that age, he ſo bleſſed their acte of genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that in conuenient time the earth was repleniſhed with people: gaue them thinges nedefull for their bodies: clothed many of them with notable vertues, and politicall excellencies: and gaue vnto ſome, the moſt comfortable ſeale of adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The ende or cauſe wherfore he gaue them, was, both to comfort them agaynſt the bitternes of that eſtraunging of him ſelfe: and alſo, by ſuche fatherly dealing, the better to allure them vnto him. In the ſeconde age of the world, or in all that ſpace of time, that was betwixt the calling of Abraham, vntill the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of Chriſt, the preparation that he vſed, conſiſteth in foure principall poyntes. Firſte, that he choſe vnto him one people, the children of Iſraell out of all the world. Whiche is ſo to be taken, as that we haue out of the ſame to gather, that for all that time, as for any Church or people of adoption, he had no other Nation, or whole Familie
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:19467:29"/> (that we knowe of) in all the worlde, but them alone: and yet that euer he had di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers particular men of other Nations, whome he had ſecretly ſealed, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ioyned vnto them, in their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion. And as for other fauourable dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, though he delt very graciouſly with others, alſo: yet was he euer moſt graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to them. Secondarily, by giuing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a farther knowledge of whatſoeuer ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perteyned to the worke of Redemption that was in hande, by that forme of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion which is termed the Law; the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes opening and vrging the ſame. as touching which we haue to conſider, firſt, what was therein exhibited vnto them: then, howe he did applie the ſame to their vſe. There were exhibited vnto them a couple of Couenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts. The one that if they ſhould performe the rule of abſolute righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, to them in the Law preſcribed, they ſhoulde bee able to liue thereby: or, which is the ſame, they ſhould be able to ſtande in the iudgement of God, by the vertue of their owne merites. The other, that forbecauſe no body was able to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme it, therefore him ſelfe had prouided
<pb facs="tcp:19467:30"/> him of an other that ſhould performe the ſame; and would ſende him into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world when the time ſhould come: on whome whoſoeuer ſhould fully reſt, and ſeeke no further, they ſhould be able to ſtande by him, and by the vertue of his merites. He applyed the ſame to their vſe two maner of wayes. Firſt, by geuing foorth the rule of abſolute righteouſnes, and requiring the full performaunce of it: or els letting them vnderſtande, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſhould be able to ſtande before him. ſo to chaſe them away from the opinion of their owne righteouſnes, that naturall hereſie of all mankinde. Then, for that by the Prophetes he both gaue them to vnderſtande, that there was an other way of ſaluation ordeyned (by the latter Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenaunt); and that there was no other but it: and alſo by often renewing of his promiſe dyd very well ſtrengthen them, both agaynſt doubtfulneſſe on the one ſide; and agaynſt the impaciencie of long wayting, on the other ſyde. Thirdely, by the figures and ſhadowes of the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiticall ceremonies: whereby he did no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably deſcribe the Sauiour; and the whole
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:19467:30"/> worke of Redemption by him. Laſt of all, about foure hundred yeeres before that the Sauiour ſhoulde come, he dyd as it were prouoke their appetite to couet him: both by geuing no Prophet or Viſion vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, as before he was wonte; and by plunging their State or Common welth in deepe diſtreſſe.</p>
               <p>To come to the ſecond, that is, the brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging forth of the worke of Redemption it ſelfe, there be foure principal things to be conſidered. firſt, what time it came in. ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condarily, what kind of one he was, and muſt nedes haue ben, that ſhuld performe it. thirdly, how he hath performed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. laſt of all, how comfortable his name is vnto vs. The time wherein he perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally came, was the latter end of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſecond age, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fulnes of time was come. ſo to performe his promiſe to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nation, before that they ſhould be caſt of from being his peculiar people. Our Sauiour was, and nedes muſt haue bene both God and man. It behoued him to be god, that he might be the perſon y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were able to doo whatſoeuer apperteined to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> work of Rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ption. It behoued him to be ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that ſo he might be
<pb facs="tcp:19467:31"/> the partie that onely was chargeable, or that might lawfully doo it, which coulde be no other but only man. In which his manhood he had experience of our infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities of nature: but was neuer ſteined with any ſpotte of ſinne. The performa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of his worke reſteth in two principall poynts. Firſt, that he hath on our behalfe ſuſteined in his manhood, whatſoeuer weight of vengeaunce was due to our ſinne: ſo to anſwere the Iuſtice of God. and yet him ſelfe periſhed not, as wee ſhould haue done, for that he was able to caſt it of when he would. Then, that he hath wrought on our behalfe whatſoeuer righteouſnes, or perfection the iuſtice of God requireth of thoſe that ſhould be left into the kingdome of God: that ſo wee might be able, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vertue of his merites, to come thervnto. As touching his name, the matter is this, that to our comforte, and to the ſtrengthening of our fayth, he would be called Ieſus Chriſt. Ieſus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an Hebrewe worde, and ſignifying a Sauiour: Chriſt being a Greeke worde, and ſignifying Annoynted. Whiche An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynting (beeing an olde ceremonie of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:19467:31"/> the Leuitical Lawe, fulfilled and abroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Chriſt) doth in him ſignifie, that he was both ordeined of God, to be our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour: and alſo furniſhed with abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to ſaue. And therefore that he is in this ſorte (moſte effectually) annoynted our Prieſt, Prophet, and King: that of his fulnes we might all receyue whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer were needefull. that is, that he beeing our Prieſt, might make the attonement for euer betwixt God and vs: he beeing our Prophet or Teacher, might inſtruct vs in all things for vs to knowe: he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our king, might gouerne, both with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in vs by his grace, or ſpirite of adoption: &amp; without vs by his power in all things els, that nothing hurt vs.</p>
               <p>The third remaineth, that is to find out, after what maner this our Sauiour, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing finiſhed all for the which he came in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world, in this thirde and laſte age of the world hath euer mainteined, and notably aduau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced this worke of Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. wherein there are three principall thinges to be conſidered. The firſt is, that notwithſtanding diuers lets or hinderan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that were in the way: yet it pleaſed
<pb facs="tcp:19467:32"/> God to aduaunce the publication of this worke of Redemption in ſuch ſort, that in time conuenient it was knowne &amp; recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued throughout the world. and ſo, all na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions inuited to the kingdome of God: or, the kingdome of God ſet open, not to one nation nowe, but to all beleeuers. The lettes that I ſpeake of, were eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially three. The nation of the Iewes: their Temple, and ceremonies yet remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in eſtimation. Moſt bitter Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for a long time after, immediately inſuing. And, when it was ceaſſed, moſt greeuous variaunce, and Hereſies, that dydde then aryſe oute of the peace and quietnes of the Churche. The ſeconde, that after this, when the people beganne generally to bee weerie of the worde of lyfe, it pleaſed hym, ſo to auenge the contempt thereof throughout the earth, that (as ſynce wee haue founde) he dyd in deede darken this fayre day maruei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous muche. in the Eaſt, and muche of the Southe, by the abhomination of Mahomet: in the Weſt and muche of the Northe, by that moſte Idolatrous vanitie of the Churche of Rome. But
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:19467:32"/> yet he euer reſerued vnto him ſelfe a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient number of witneſſes, to teſtifie the truth to the wicked worlde, euen in the corrupteſt time of all, or whenſoeuer the power of darknes moſte preuayled. The thirde and laſte, that nowe to the comforte of all his people, he dothe glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly aduaunce the Goſpell agayne, to wake vs vp agaynſt his comming: and euery day, more and more dothe nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly purge it from the ruſte and cancre, that corruption of time had brought vnto it; and mightely enlargeth the beames of the truth, to lighte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al, in al things nedeful.</p>
               <p>Hauing ſo declared, both in what ſorte he beganne, and after what maner hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to he proceeded in this manifeſtation of himſelfe, now haue we to ſearch out, what muſt be the accompliſhment, or finiſhing of it. Concerning which, he hath geuen vs before hande to vnderſtande, that when the time appoynted ſhal come, then ſhalbe the day of generall iudgement, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he wyll finiſhe the whole worke. Heer therefore haue wee particularly to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider theſe fiue principall thinges. Firſt, what is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time appoynted, then, who they
<pb facs="tcp:19467:33"/> are that muſt come to iudgment. thirdly, in what maner the iudgement ſhall be. fourthly, what kinde of execution ſhall follow. laſt of all, howe Chriſt ſhall then reſigne or gyue vp his kingdome to his Father againe.</p>
               <p>As touching the tyme that I ſpeake of, firſt of all we haue certaine likelihoodes, that it is lyke to be now very nere. Then alſo, we haue this vndoubted know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that it ſhall be, ſo ſone as God ſhall haue brought in the full number of his choſen people; and finiſhed all thinges els that he had in his purpoſe to doe.</p>
               <p>Thoſe that muſte come to iudgement, are, euen all, and euery one, without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of dignitie, ſexe, age, or ſuche like, that euer were, are, or ſhalbe hereafter to that preſent day. al which (by y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> time y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the whole accompt be made) may come vnder a couple of ſortes. The firſte is of thoſe that are departed before that tyme. who muſte all, whether their ſoules were in wretchedneſſe, or in bleſſed eſtate, haue their owne bodyes reſtored to them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. to thende, that as Soule and Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy haue communicated together in ſuche
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:19467:33"/> thinges as they haue done: ſo may they both together haue their iudgement. The other is of thoſe that ſhall liue at that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. who ſhall, firſt ſodenly be chaunged and made ſuch, as thoſe are, that are riſen againe: and then with the reſte receaue their iudgement.</p>
               <p>As touching the maner of that iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, we are geuen to vnderſtande, that, our Sauiour ſhall come in greate glorie: the heauens and the earth ſhal paſſe at his preſence: all mankinde ſhall be diuided or ſundred into a couple of ſeuerall partes: &amp; the hearts of all being plainely opened, he ſhall pronounce, euerlaſting ioyes or bleſſedneſſe to the one; euerlaſting tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes or wretchednes to the other.</p>
               <p>The execution that ſhall be done, ſhalbe according to the ſentence pronounced. the one ſorte caſte downe, with the diuels to hell: the other taken vp, with him ſelfe to heauen. The reſignatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his kingdome is, that ſo hauing finiſhed all, he ſhal from that day forward rule no more as media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor (becauſe he hath finiſhed that worke): but euer notwithſtanding as he is God, and equall to the Father.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:19467:34"/>
               <head>The Perſon of the Holy Ghoſt.</head>
               <p>VVto the Perſon of the holy Ghoſt we attribute the working of his purpoſe aforeſaid in vs, and in all other creatures of the worlde, as his wiſedome knoweth to be moſt agreable to that his purpoſe, and to the bringing forth of the ſame to his owne glory. Of this working of gods holy ſpirit, I finde two principall ſortes. whereof the former is that generall wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of his, whereby the vniuerſall ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of all thinges in this world continueth in ſuche ſort as we ſee that it doth. The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is that wherby he is occupied in ſome ſpeciall kinde.</p>
               <p>Of that his generall working withal, the principall actions are, that whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer there is in the world, from the higheſt to the loweſt, that doth he firſt vpholde &amp; mainteine, vntill the tyme appoynted do come that he will haue the ſame diſſolued. Secondarily he doth direct, guide, and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſame; that all thinges fall out, not at auenture: but as God him ſelfe in his
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:19467:34"/> ſecret purpoſe hath ordeyned; as well for the tyme; as alſo for the maner of iſſue. Thirdly that he doth vnite, couple, or knit together all in one, with certaine bandes of mutuall ſocietie, ſo farre as the kind or nature of euery one may beare. and that on the nedefull behalfe, both of the whole; and of euery membre or part.</p>
               <p>Of his working with ſome ſpeciall kind, there are three principal ſortes. The firſte and principall is the ſame that hee beſtoweth on his choſen or peculiar peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. the ſeconde, that which he caſteth vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the reprobate, or caſt-away ſeede, the third, the ſame whereby he worketh in all inferior creatures.</p>
               <p>As touching his working with the cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, there are fyue principall thinges to be conſidered. firſte, what the worke it ſelfe is that he worketh in them: ſecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darily, howe farre he worketh in them the ſame y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hee worketh: thirdly, by what de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees he doth it: fourthly, by what power: laſt of all to what ende or purpoſe.</p>
               <p>To find out what the worke it ſelfe is, we haue to conſider howe hee worketh in them. firſte as they are menne; then as
<pb facs="tcp:19467:35"/> they are his electe nombre, or choyce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flocke.</p>
               <p>As they are men, his worke in them is no more, but that which conſiſteth in thoſe three poyntes of his generall working with all: that ſo he may make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in thoſe things alſo, conuenient members of their common ſocietie with all thinges els. Which is that he, according as he thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth good, doth vpholde and mainteine them; guide &amp; order them; and knit them together as behoueth.</p>
               <p>As we are his choyce-flocke, he beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth on vs an excellent worke. For ſeeing that we are ordeyned or choſen to be an holy people, a peculiar inheritaunce, a kingdome of prieſtes, and citizens of the kingdome of God, therfore doth he frame vs to be ſuche as may become ſo holy a calling. And yet in ſuch ſorte, that firſt as touching naturall corruption he leaueth the ſame wholly vnto vs. wherein not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding is to be conſidered, that as by the force of it we both euer are geuen vnto ſinne; and alſo muche and often of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend: ſo on the other ſide, doth he ſo migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely bridle y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, that it doth not reigne
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:19467:35"/> in vs, or is not ſo ſtrong againſt vs, that it preuaileth to our deſtruction. Then as touching the ſpirituall working of his grace that we may be decked with conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient beauty, and ſuch excellencies as our ſelues haue not, he doth both lay as it were the foundation thereof; and alſo rayſeth vp a goodly building vppon the ſame. The foundation that hee layeth, is that he doth effectually call vs, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gette vs againe, or renue our mindes. which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſteth in two principall pointes. firſte, that he doth notably tranſlate vs from the barreine and corrupte moulde where before we griewe, the original cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of our nature, and that, not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſte, or without our willes: but with hartie miſliking of our former reprobate wayes. Then, that he planteth vs in Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt: or graffeth vs into him, or into his fleſhe, or manhood by miſtical vnion. The building that is layd vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſteth of many notable vertues. wherof ſome are Capitall, or more gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall: others more ſpeciall, or ſuche as ariſe out of thoſe others. The general vertues are theſe firſt, a good &amp; a ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d knowledge
<pb facs="tcp:19467:36"/> of the Sonne, &amp; the holy ghoſt then, a ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led &amp; a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmed iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t (in ſuch things as concerne our ſaluation) forth-with ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing out of this knowledge. thirdly, a fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent &amp; a ſingular loue of God, for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we fynd him to be ſuch as he is. fourthly, to ſettle our ſelues wholly in him, both for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole worke of our redemption; and for whatſoeuer els we nede. laſt of all, ſuch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, humilitie, or pliablenes of mind, as y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> puting by, both man one the one ſide; and all other creatures in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or earth on the other ſide: we doe a kinde of ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Homage, or ſoueraigne ſeruice to God, geuing ouer our ſelues wholly to him, to do whatſoeuer we ſhall finde that he requireth. Thoſe other vertues that are more ſpeciall, or goe more directly to ſome point of our dutie, are of two ſortes or companies. ſuche as doe concerne that parte of our dutie that the ſpirite of God in vs worketh forth to Gods owne per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: and ſuch as it worketh forth towards the common ſocietie wherein we lyue. Of the firſte ſorte there are three. Fyrſte that we worſhippe him, not as our ſelues, or others thinke good: but onely as him
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:19467:36"/> ſelfe hath appoynted. The ſeconde, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſame manner of our worſhipping be not counterfet or diſſembled: but ſyncere, or inwardely ſuche, as outwardely, we doo pretende. The thirde, that to the ende we may attaine therevnto, we be not eyther altogether careleſſe of the ſame; or, but after a common maner bent vnto it: but that we be ſo earneſtly ſet therevppon, as that we do very dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly vſe ſuch things as lead therevnto. Of the other ſort there are lykewiſe other three. whiche are, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly to beare ſuche a loue or affection to all and to euery one as that firſte we vnite or knitte our ſelues together to all and to euery one, in ſuche ſorte as God ſhall appoint: whether they be Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, vnworthy, or our enemies. Secon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darily, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſtudie the preſeruation of all and of euery one. and that not onely Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally, that in all thinges it be well with them: but alſo more ſpecially in theſe three pointes, his wedlocke, Subſtaunce, and good Name, laſt of al that we ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent oure ſelues with oure owne eſtate whatſoeuer it be, that we neuer couet to ſteppe into any others.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19467:37"/>
               <p>As touching the ſecond poynt, that is, how farre he worketh in them theſe moſt excellent graces, we haue to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider theſe two thinges. Firſt, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> perſon of Chriſt all theſe thinges be moſte abſolutely wrought: not one iote of them all wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. ſo that as we are in him, we haue moſte perfect righteouſnes wrought: yf not in vs; yet for vs, and on our behalfe. Then, that as we conſider our ſelues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parte (and yet as we are in Chriſt) it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth God to worke in vs, not all thoſe thinges aboue rehearſed; nor any greate perfection that commeth neere therevn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to: but only a certaine mediocritie that is very farre diſtant in euery poynt (euen in thoſe wherevnto we come nereſt of all) from the perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that here is deſcribed. and this, in ſome more, in ſome leſſe, and for the moſte part maruelous litle. when he worketh theſe things more abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it is to ſhew forth how litle y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our nature is able to preuaile againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> power of his grace, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſoeuer he is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed effectually to worke therby. whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he worketh theſe things ſo ſparingly, it is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glory of his free gift be leſſe darkned by
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:19467:37"/> the goodnes that he ſhould worke in vs.</p>
               <p>Concerning the third poynt, that is, by what degrees he worketh theſe things in the choſen or faithfull ſo far as it pleaſeth him to work them, we haue to vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d; Firſt of all, that he geueth the motion, or bringeth to minde that which he is diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to worke in them. Secondarily, that he kindleth in them a liking of the ſame. Thirdly, that he trameth in their willes a conſent and readines to do it. Laſtly, that he worketh in them: or, bringeth foorth that motion, liking, and readines to doo it, to the deede it ſelfe.</p>
               <p>As touching the fourth poynt, that is, by what power he worketh the ſame, we haue to conſider, that there are a couple of kindes thereof: the one inwarde: the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther outwarde. That which is inwarde, is the principall: and is that mercifull po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of God, which alſo is called the grace of Ieſus Chriſt. which hauing in vs, my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtically, the like function, office, or nature, as the blood hath with the body, or the ſappe with the tree, doth ſo make vs fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in ſuch things as are acceptable and welcome to God. That whiche is out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde,
<pb facs="tcp:19467:38"/> is the ſame that he putteth foorth in thoſe Meanes, and Helpes, whereby he worketh.</p>
               <p>Concerning the meanes that I ſpeake of, wee haue to conſider theſe two thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. firſte, what the meanes are: then, howe it pleaſeth the holy Ghoſt to worke by them. The meanes are foure, the worde; the Sacramentes; the Churche; and Gouernement. Vnder the worde is to be vnderſtoode, principally the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures, that is, the Olde, and the Newe Teſtamentes: then alſo whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer other inſtruction agreeth therwithall; whether it bee Publique, or Priuate. Publique inſtruction is that which is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in open audience, or by publique authoritie: as ordinarie Seruice, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, Sermons. Priuate is that whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che paſſeth in mutuall conference, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene one man an an other. The two Sacramentes, or Pledges, or Viſible witneſſinges of the Couenaunt of Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption made by god with al true beleuers, are Baptiſme, and the Lordes Supper. Whereof the one dothe witneſſe that we are made cleane, and graffed into the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:19467:38"/> of Chriſte: the other that we haue in him all manner of fulneſſe, or ſufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie for our Redemption. The Churche is no more, but the ſocietie or fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe of thoſe that doo profeſſe the fayth of Chriſt, and therefore euer haue among them his worde, and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, in high eſtimation. whiche, as we eſteeme it one of the Meanes, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the holy Ghoſt worketh in vs ſuche thinges as apperteyne to our Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is<note n="*" place="margin">The mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this limitation is this firſt that wee take not into this accompt that parte of the Church which is Triumphant, becauſe they are ſeuered from vs, and we haue no warrant that in theſe things it pleaſeth God to helpe vs by them: but Militaunt, or thoſe that are in their warfare heere on the earth. Secondarily, that we doo not diſcontent our ſelues, yf wee can not lay before our eyes the vniuerſall or whole Churche at once, for that ſo we coulde haue no dealing at all with them: but content our ſelues with the Nationall Churche that is about vs, for that we may haue dealing with it, and by it (if it bee ſuche as is deſcribed) bee knitte to the whole. Thirdly, that this Churche neede not be that whiche is termed inuiſible, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting onely of the truer members, whiche are knowne onely to God, and not vnto vs: but that we neede no other whereby the holy Ghoſt ſhoulde worke, but onely that which is viſible, or thoſe that profeſſe Chriſtianitie, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it bee truely, or not: for that by their outwarde profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, the holy Ghoſt can wel ynough bring vs to the truth.</note> Militaunt, National, &amp; Viſible.
<pb facs="tcp:19467:39"/> Of Gouernment there be three ſortes. Firſt, that whiche is eſtabliſhed in euery State, and is diſtributed from the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne three maner of wayes, and ſo ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the name of<note n="*" place="margin">Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche is occupied a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>naunceme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or maintei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce of religion. Ci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uile it is, as it is occupi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed in caſes of common equitie, in a peaceable and quiet ſtate. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall, or ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med it is, as it ſeeth to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> defence of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwelth, by lande, and ſea, at home, and abroade.</note> Eccleſiaſtical, Ciuill, &amp; Martiall. Secondarily, that whiche is meerely ſpirituall, and is taken vp in any congregation of their owne accord, and is called diſcipline, or the vſe of the keies. Wherein are three principal thinges to be conſidered, the forme, the force, and the vſe thereof. Vnto the forme apperteineth the conſideration of theſe three. Firſt, of the perſons in whoſe handes it is: which are of the better and godlyer ſorte; and ſuch as them ſelues can like of to be ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by. Secondarily, by what they go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne: whiche is, by no maner of ciuile correction: but only by the wiſe &amp; righte applying of the worde, and the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, when it is done by the ordinarie miniſter; otherwiſe, onely by applying the word in mutual conference. Thirdly, what direction is left the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to leade them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right: whiche is no more, but ſometimes their owne conſcience or iudgement; ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times certayne canons, decrees, or rules
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:19467:39"/> agreed vpon among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al. The force of it is, neither to wrap offenders in any ciuile and worldly vengeaunce; nor to reward well-doers with any ciuile and worldly recompence: but to pearce into the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of bothe; and to ſhewe them in what caſe they ſtande before God in ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall accompt: and ſo reſtrayneth, not the wilfull, or ſuche as haue not the feare of God; but onely the willing, and ſuch as haue the touche of conſcience. The vſe of this kinde of gouernment is. not onely when the other gouernement eſtabliſhed is agaynſt Chriſt; but alſo when it goeth not in all poynts with the ſinceritie of the worde. and therfore, nedefull in all ſtates; and euer in vre with the godlyer: and yet not going agaynſt the other gouernment eſtabliſhed; nor any thing at al preiudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al thervnto. Thirdly, that which we ſee in euery good familie: which we may terme domeſticall. Whereby parentes gouerne their children, Scholemaſters their ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, and maſters their ſeruauntes.</p>
               <p>The maner of the holy Ghoſtes wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king by theſe is this. By the worde he di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recteth vs in all thinges nedefull. For as
<pb facs="tcp:19467:40"/> touching doctrine, he riddeth vs from all damnable opinions: and teacheth vs all needefull truth. In maners, he dothe ſo clenſe vs from ill, that alſo we loth it: and doth ſo frame vs to goodnes, that he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clineth our harts towards it. By the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes he confirmeth vnto vs the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenaunte of mercy, and eſtabliſheth our fayth in the ſame: ſo to reape the fruite therof. by Baptiſme, that we are made the children of God, and knit vnto Chriſt; and that euer our hold therin is renewed, as neede requireth: by the Lordes Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, that we haue plentifull Redemption in Chriſt Ieſus; and that we ſeeke it one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in him. By the ſocietie that wee haue with the Church, becauſe him ſelfe dothe moſte preſently rule there, and hath the Scepter of his kingdome among them, by it he bringeth vs to ſome proofe. For beſides the benefite of the worde and the Sacramentes whiche wee finde among them; he otherwiſe getteth vs forwarde, and carrieth vs vp to further perfection. for that, by their good example he fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth vs to doo the like: by their go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement keepeth vs in order: and by
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:19467:40"/> their conſent, company, and felowſhippe doth much ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gthen vs in many things. By thoſe three ſortes of gouernment, he reſtrayneth our vnruly nature: incoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth vs in the way of godlines: keepeth vs in, that we breake not out: ordereth vs in good and ſeemely maner: and lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vs the way to euerlaſting peace.</p>
               <p>Concerning thoſe helpes that I ſpeake of, wee haue in lyke ſorte to ſee, Firſte, what they are: then, howe it pleaſeth God to worke by them. The Helpes are three: Watchinge, Faſtinge, and Prayer. Watchinge is, diligentlye too keepe our ſoules, or to ſee to our ſelues. and therefore to bee well aduyſed of theſe two thinges: what maye hynder vs in the waye of godlyneſſe; and what maye further vs in the ſame. Faſting is eyther Publique, or Priuate. Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique is eyther a generall mournynge in the tyme of ſome Calamitie, eyther appearing, or preſent: or elſe a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall endeuour or ſtyrring vppe of oure ſelues when ſome weightie matter is too bee attempted. Pryuate is ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Ordinarie, or Extraordinarie.
<pb facs="tcp:19467:41"/> Ordinarie faſting is, all our whole life to liue ſoberly, or to vſe great moderation, partly in things needefull: but eſpecially in ſuch things as apperteine to delectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Extraordinarie is, when wee haue founde our ſelues more prone vnto ſinne, or flowe to goodnes then we were wont, then to auoyde the occaſions of ill, and to vſe the occaſions of goodnes. Prayer is the lifting vp of the hartes vnto God, when we haue ſenſibly founde, our ſelues to be nothing. him only to be all in all.</p>
               <p>The maner of his working by theſe, is this. By watching, that wee doe eſpie what things may hinder vs; what things may further vs. By Faſting that auoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the occaſions of yll, we auoyde the yll too: and vſing the occaſions of well dooing, wee alſo winne to the thing it ſelfe. By Prayer he geueth, (as neede is) from aboue, that whiche we haue not here beneath.</p>
               <p>The laſte poynte of his working in the Choſen is to conſider, to what ende or purpoſe he ſo worketh in them. Which is, not to ſhewe foorth howe good they are in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pariſon of others (as though by
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:19467:41"/> their goodnes he were firſt prouoked ſo to deale with them; when as in dede theſe were at the firſt no better then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates): but to ſhew forth, as mete it was, him ſelfe onely. that is, his ſecrete pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe as touching them: the depth of his mercy: and many other poyntes of his Glorie.</p>
               <p>The ſeconde poynt of his ſpeciall wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, is the ſame which he beſtoweth on the Reprobate. As touching whiche, we haue in like ſorte to conſider, firſt, what he worketh in them: ſecondarily, in what qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>titie or meaſure he worketh the ſame: thirdly, by what degrees he worketh it in them: fourthly, howe he dothe it, or by what power or meanes: laſt of al, to what ende or purpoſe he ſo worketh in them.</p>
               <p>To finde out what he worketh in them, we haue to enter into a double conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. firſt, what he worketh in them as they are Men: then, what he worketh in them as they are Reprobates.</p>
               <p>As they are Men, and ſo a parte of our common ſocietie ſo long as they liue, he worketh ſo in them, as that they may bee conueniente members of our Societie,
<pb facs="tcp:19467:42"/> euery one as he is ordeined to be: whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be to leade them to that which they ſhould do; or to reſtrayne them from that which they ſhould not doo. and therefore mainteineth, vniteth, &amp; guideth them alſo.</p>
               <p>As they are Reprobates, and ſo not or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deined to haue any portio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with Chriſt, but to goe on their owne way to euerlaſting perdition, the effect of his working with them reſteth in two principall poyntes. that is to conſider, what goodnes on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the one ſide he worketh in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: and on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other ſide, what iniquitie of their owne he wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth forth out of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or bringeth to light. Concerning the goodnes that he worketh in them, we haue to knowe, that firſt as touching any true godlines, ſuch as ſhall be accepted with God, he neuer planteth them in Chriſt, nor tranſlateth them from the corruption of their owne nature. and ſo conſequently, neuer worketh in them, eyther thoſe Capitall vertues before re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſed: or thoſe other Braunches that ſhould proceede out of the ſame. So that theſe, all their whole life time, bee their yeeres neuer ſo many, haue not one iote of true godlines in Deede, worde, or
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:19467:42"/> Thought. Then as touching a ſeconda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie kinde of goodnes, he doth in dede both bring to paſſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whatſoeuer they do (euen their moſt wicked ſinnes of all) ſhal ſome way or other do good vnto others, or be to very good vſe howe ſoeuer it fal: &amp; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo worketh in them two ſortes of things, that are to good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendation vnto them in the eye of man. Firſt, diuers worthy and notable qualities: eyther Natural, or Ciuile. Then alſo certaine apparances or likelyhoodes of thoſe ſpiritual, and ſound graces that he worketh in the choſen; or thoſe graces vnperfect or maymed. as namely, a certaine kinde or likenes of our vnion with Chriſt: a certaine kind or ſhew of thoſe Capitall vertues; knowledge; ſoundnes of Iudgement; Loue; Fayth; and pliablenes of minde: and a certayne kinde or ſhewe of al thoſe other particular vertues, that are before ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly recited. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the other, that is, what iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie he worketh forth out of them, or howe he hardeneth them in their owne corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or leaueth the ſame forcible agaynſt themſelues, we haue to conſider, that firſt as touching the Capitall vices that are
<pb facs="tcp:19467:43"/> contrary to thoſe Capitall vertues before ſet downe, he hampereth them in their owne ſnares, or ſullieth them with their owne vncleannes. which is, firſt, a deepe Ignoraunce (and that very wilfull) of God the Father, the Sonne, and the holy ghoſt. Secondarily, a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſed iudgement, and a monſtrous opinion in all thinges. Thirdly, an inwarde &amp; a naturall lothing of God, ſo far as they dare; or are not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained by earthly benefites. Fourthly, Infidelitie, or, not ſoundly to reſt in him. Laſt of all, an inuincible frowardnes or hardnes of harte, or a proude loftines of mind: vtterly refuſing to put by man, and other creatures, that ſo they mighte geue them ſelues wholly and onely vnto the Lorde: and euer coupling all together in ſuch ſort, that although in their fonde fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie they eſteme them not all alike; yet doo they bothe make thoſe others no better then Idolles, and wickedly robbe God of his glory. Then as touching a couple of. Braunches that are contrarie to thoſe before recited, and doo growe or ſpring out of thoſe Capitall vices? firſte, as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching thoſe that goe directly agaynſt the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:19467:43"/> honour of Gods owne perſon, to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him as themſelues or other like them ſelues, will: to haue very ſawcie or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reuerent heartes before him: and to bee careles of ſounde deuotion. then, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the others that do apperteine to the common Societie that god hath ſet amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vs, diſdainefully to deſpiſe the ſame, little rogarding howe notably they are inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red thereunto: to haue no care of preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, as in generall, ſo likewiſe parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularlye, neither of their neighbours wedlocke; nor of his ſubſtaunce, nor of his goode name or eſtimation: and euer to be diſco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent with ſuch preſent eſtate, as it pleaſed God to caſt vpon them.</p>
               <p>The ſeconde poynte of his working with the Reprobate as they are Rebro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates, is to finde out, in what quantitie or meaſure he worketh foorth this their iniquitie. which he doth, in ſome more: in ſome leſſe: in euery one, and in all to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, as his wiſdome hath founde moſt expedient, eyther to execute on them his iuſte iudgementes; or by them to exerciſe his choſen; or otherwiſe to doo his wyll and pleaſure.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19467:44"/>
               <p>Thirdly, we haue to examine by what degrees he worketh in them. whiche are all one with thoſe others that we ſpake of before. For out of their owne ſtoare he ſtyrreth vp or bringeth forth, firſt the Motion: ſecondarily the lyking: thirdly a Readines to do it: laſt of all, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting of the acte it ſelfe.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, we haue to conſider in what maner, or by what power or meanes he worketh this ſame in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. which alſo hath a double conſideration. Inwardly he doth it two wayes. partly by the miniſterie of Sathan: and partly by their owne redi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to yll. By both which he dealeth with them two maner of waies. The one is, by making ſtrong or forcible vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them their owne natural corruption, geuing them o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to be lead thereby, as before is deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed. The other is by ſetting them (as them ſelues alſo weigh thervnto) in thoſe ſhewes or ſhadowes of ſounde excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies before recited (as if they were the things them ſelues) till their deſtruction come vppon them before they be ware. Outwardly, inſtrumentally, or in reſpect of the outwarde action he doth it by two
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:19467:44"/> poyntes of their owne corruption. The one is the great contempte that they haue as well of thoſe ordinarie Meanes, the Worde, the Sacramentes, the Churche, and Gouernment: as alſo of the Helpes before recyted, Watching, Faſting, and Prayer. The other is that highe and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate eſtimation that they haue of deceiptfull groundes: whiche are naught els but Fleſhe and Blood, or an arme of Fleſhe. as the ouer-laſhing opinion which in theſe dayes a number of them haue of their owne iudgement, the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of man, Antiquitie, Vniuerſalitie, Doctors, Councels, Succeſſion of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, Tradition of elders, Churche of Rome, Peters fayth, and ſuch like.</p>
               <p>Laſt of al is to be ſeene, to what ende he doth ſo worke in them. which neuer is, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the ſinnes ſake to helpe forwarde ſinne; or to bring vpon them other ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie then them ſelues would willingly fall into: but euer to bring vpon them, in the way of iuſt vengeaunce, the fruites of their owne vngracious wayes; to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute his owne righteous Iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts; and to ſhewe foorth his pacience or longe-ſuffering,
<pb facs="tcp:19467:45"/> and other poyntes of his glory beſides.</p>
               <p>The thirde and laſt poynt of his ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all working is the ſame whereby he dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth with all inferiour Creatures ordey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the vſe of man. In which (conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering that which is ſayde alreadie of his generall worke withall) wee haue but theſe two thinges to conſider. firſt, what is the maner of his working in them: and then the ende wherevnto it tendeth. The maner of his working in them, is eyther by the common courſe of nature whiche he hath already ſet or appoynted to euery one: or by ſome Extraordinarie or ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret power, beſides the courſe of nature; or els cleane contrarie therevnto. The ende whervnto this his working tendeth is, eyther to do that whervnto by courſe of nature thoſe things are ordeyned: or els to doo ſome extraordinarie thing o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe then the courſe of nature lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth them vnto. Whiche lightly is, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the helpe of the afflicted: or to the puniſhment of malefactors: or to the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting foorth of Gods glory.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:19467:45"/>
               <head>The Concluſion.</head>
               <p>SO we ſee, that as touching the whole worke of our rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ption, or whatſoeuer good thing is wrought in the choſen, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in the tyme of darkenes we haue take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> much to our ſelues, &amp; euer by nature couet ſo to do in theſe thinges aboue all others: yet doth it all, and euery iote ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perteine vnto God. For firſt, as touching that parte of it, that is attributed to the Father, we ſee very plainely, that ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can haue nothing to do with it. The election or purpoſe muſt needes be of God alone: no iote of it can any way apperteine vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to man. Then, as touching the ſeconde parte, whiche was the working forth of that his election or purpoſe; that muſte needes be attributed to the Sonne: and is ſuche a thing, as can not in any wiſe come vnder the fingering of man. Laſt of all, concerning the third part which was the working of the ſame in vs; that is of ſuch a nature, &amp; ſo far paſſeth the ſtrength of fleſhe and blood, that no parte thereof can properly be attributed to man but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:19467:46"/> vnto the holy<note n="*" place="margin">Neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoughe there is no good thing at all wro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ught in vs (be it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo litle: euen to the leaſt thought of all) but that in reſpecte of the ſubſtaunce of it, or doing the ſame, doth only apperteine to the Spirite of God, as to the only autor thereof: yet diuers thinges that doe apperteine to this laſte part, God doth in his worde (after a ſorte, or in ſome reſpect) intitle to man as name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, firſt, becauſe they are wrought in vs, as in the ſhoppes or working houſes of the holy Ghoſte. ſecondarily, becauſe the holy Ghoſte doth euer firſt frame our willes to go therewith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all. laſte of all, becauſe we ſhall haue the rewarde that apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teineth therevnto by the promiſſe of God. And yet not ſo, that he betrayeth his owne glory, wrongfully geuing the ſame to whom it doth not apperteine (being euer redy, yf ſo it be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to chalenge it wholly vnto him ſelfe): but only, eyther to our comfort, for that ſo he geueth vs hope of Retribulation or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde: or to our encouragement, for that ſo geuing vs the name to haue done ſomewhat, or geuing vs the prayſe of the deede, he doth allure vs with better chiere to go on forward.</note> Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Of him, and through him, and for him are all thinges. to whome be glorie for euer. Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. <hi>E.</hi> 36.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:19467:46"/>
            <head>A SHORT SVMME of Chriſtian Religion <hi>vnder the conſideration of the <hi>Ten-Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes.</hi>
               </hi>
            </head>
            <p>¶ There is none ende of making many books: and much reading is a weri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the fleſhe. Let vs heare the ende of al. Feare god &amp; kepe <hi>his Commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes:</hi> For this is the <hi>Whole</hi> dutie of man.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:19467:47"/>
            <head>A SHORT SVMME <hi>of Christian religion</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the conſideration of the <hi>ten Commaundementes. <hi>¶ The generall diſcourſe of all together.</hi>
               </hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat peece of ſcripture which commonly goeth vnder the name of the ten Commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, as is writen in the twenteth Chapter of Exo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus, from the beginning of the ſeconde, vnto the ende of the ſeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tienth verſe, may well be diuided into a couple of principal partes. wherof the former is the Preface, or fore-ſpeache vnto the Commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes: the other the Commaundements them ſelues.</p>
            <p>In the Preface, <hi>I am the Lord thy God: which brought thee out of the lande of Egypt, out of the houſe of bondage,</hi> we haue to conſider two thinges: to whome he ſpeaketh; and what it is that he ſayth vnto them. Concerning the former of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:19467:47"/> them, it is no more but this: that literally he ſpeaketh to the Iſraelites onely: Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicatiuely, or, in ſenſe and meaning, to vs alſo, and to all the faithfull, or to all Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s that haue bene ſince in al ages. Concerning the other, firſte in plaine wordes hee doth not onely ſay or affirme, that, he is the lord our God: but alſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, as he brought y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lites literally out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> land of Egipt, the houſe of bondage; ſo hath he miſtically in in lyke ſorte broughte both them and vs out of perdition, from the power of the diuell vnder whom we ſhould otherwiſe haue bene: a more wretched bondage then any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s heart could euer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceaue. Then, beſides his plaine wordes he ſemeth to implie, firſt for his owne part, that He is ſuche, as may very well commaunde vs; and we ſuch, as ought by good right obey him: ſo to make plaine vnto vs before hande, that yf he ſhall nowe geue or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe vnto vs lawes of religion, it is no more then he may lawfully do. then for all others whatſoeuer, that they haue no au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie to preſcribe vs any lawes of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; and, yf needes they wyll, yet
<pb facs="tcp:19467:48"/> neede not we obey them, nor may yf we woulde: becauſe they are not able to cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge that kinde of dutie by any ſuche ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle; and are not able truely to ſay, <hi>I am the Lord thy God. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Commaundementes them ſelues may in like maner be diuided into a cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of principall partes: ſetting the firſte by it ſelfe: and all the reſt likewiſe aparte by them ſelues, but (in this reſpect) all coupled together.</p>
            <p>The firſte Commaundement doth geue forth the Summe of all Religion Generally, or in fewe wordes compry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the whole: bringing all to this one pointe: To worſhippe, or eſteeme as God, the onely true God, and lyuinge Lorde.</p>
            <p>The other doe more Specially intreate of the ſame: diuiding this whole duty of man, or this whole ſumme of ſounde Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion into a couple of principall partes.</p>
            <p>The former of them is that part of our dutie, that immediately reſpecteth God him ſelfe: or, the worſhippe that he reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth to his owne Perſon. vnto whiche, the three next commaundementes do ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perteine.
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:19467:48"/> Of which three, the firſte decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth what kinde of worſhippe it muſt be, as touching the nature, or maner, or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce of it: that is, to worſhippe him as he hath appointed, and none otherwiſe. The ſeconde teacheth vs that we may not reſt in any outwarde ſhewe of worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping: but that we ſhoulde inwardly haue ſo notable a reuerence of God, as that ſuche worſhippe as the former deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth, ſhoulde euer be pouldred with true ſinceritie. The laſte requyreth a feruent zeale, or an vnfeined and an heartie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier to attaine therevnto, by keeping ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Sabbath day.</p>
            <p>The other reſpecteth that parte of our dutie that concerneth oure mutuall or common ſocietie, or the order of our lyfe one with an other. whiche alſo is our dutie to God: becauſe hee hath enioyned the ſame; and we otherwiſe ſtande bound to none but to him. Of which the other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ixe Commaundementes doe entreate. and that in ſuche ſorte, that, firſte they all conſidered together doo plainely im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ly, that firſte we muſte haue an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde Loue, or an heartie affection,
<pb facs="tcp:19467:49"/> both to the whole, and to euery membre thereof: then that we muſt bring forth the ſame three maner of wayes. Whereof the the firſt is, that we knit or linke together one with an other, in ſuch order, as it ſhal appeare that God him ſelfe from time to tyme doth ſet among vs: vnto which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perteineth the fifte Commaundement. The ſeconde, that vnto this knitting to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether by honouring each other, we alſo bring with vs a true and faythfull care of preſeruation, to be ſpread forth vnto all, &amp; to euery one. This doth God commende vnto vs two maner of wayes. firſt gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, or in fewe wordes compriſing the whole charge: wherevnto apperteineth the ſixt commaundement. then more ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, or deſcending to ſome particulars: vnto whiche apperteine thoſe three that next followe. whereof the firſt, requireth ſo good regard of euery one, as that we anoy none in their wedlocke; or, that our ſelues walke not ſo inordinately in that kinde of vice, that it be, eyther the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwing or els y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> daungering of others: the ſeconde likewiſe, ſo vnfeyned a care of our neighbour, that we ſeeke not wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:19467:49"/> to get fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him any thing that is his: the thirde in like maner, ſo good aduice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on his behalfe, that we euer ſeeke to vpholde our neighbours good name and eſtimation. The third and laſt is, that we be euer fully content with our eſtate: that ſo our common Societie may be leſſe vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated by any inordinate dealing to better our ſelues; vnto which the laſt Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement doth apperteine, and therewithal maketh the way more eaſie to the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of all the reſt.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The particular diſcourſe of euery one.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The first Commaundement.</head>
                  <p>THe firſt Commaundement, as before is declared, doth geue forth the whole dutie of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or the whole ſumme of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion Generally: bringing the whole, within the compaſſe of theſe fewe words; To haue no other Gods in the ſight of the onely true &amp; liuing Lord. But for the further opening of it, we haue to
<pb facs="tcp:19467:50"/> conſider theſe two things. firſt, what it forbiddeth: then, what it requireth.</p>
                  <p>It forbiddeth, firſt the vice it ſelfe, that here is named: then alſo the Roote therof, and whatſoeuer increaſe commeth out of the ſame firſt, that ſo this vice may out of it afterwarde more naturally ſpring, and laſt of all the ſoyle wherein it groweth. The vice that here is named is, to haue mo Gods, then him that is in dede y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> only God: whether they be creatures in dede; or but fictions of their owne deuiſe. The Roote is, and needes muſt be, the Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce of God; the Father, the Sonne, &amp; the holy Ghoſt. Which what it is, as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the<note n="*" place="margin">The par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars are but touched briefly in that which followeth. but largely in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer booke, which goth altogether he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>vpon.</note> particulars therof, may be more conueniently gathered out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> knowlege anone to be ſet downe. Out of this igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce doth ſpring that which is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly called vnbeleefe, or hardnes of hart, or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitencie (when we take thoſe wordes more largely): which in effect is, firſt a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed &amp; a wrong iudgement in all thinges that apperteine to ſound Religion: ſecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darily, little or nothing to eſteme of God: thirdly, neuer ſoundly to reſt in him, but ſtil to preſſe on further, we wote not whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: laſt of al ſo ſtubberne &amp; ſo frowarde
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:19467:50"/> an hart, that refuſing to ſubmit our ſelues wholy to God, we huddle him and others together, as we thinke good; and ſo geue forth nothing but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which is, either plainly wicked, or els, vnder the ſhew of holynes, as bad. The ſoyle or grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d wherin it gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth is the corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our nature. which corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reigneth in al Infidels: not only with the worſt; but alſo with thoſe that are the very beſt among them.</p>
                  <p>It requireth, firſt the vertue it ſelfe that heere is named: then alſo bothe the Roote oute of whiche it commeth, and whatſoeuer other increaſe groweth out of the ſame, before that this vertue can naturally ſpring: and laſt of al the ground wherin it groweth. The vertue is, to put by all others, &amp; to haue the true God only to be our god. Thoſe that we haue to put by, are firſt all maner of creatures. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Celeſtiall, as Angels, or Saintes: or of this world, as our ſelues, or others, our own, or other folks excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cies, the ſunne, the moone, beaſtes, birdes, fiſhes, plants, ymages, &amp; ſuche like: or Infernall, as the deuils or ill ſpirits; &amp; da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned ſoules Then alſo all chimers, or fictions, or imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, or conceiptes of our owne brayne:
<pb facs="tcp:19467:51"/> as when the Heatheniſhe people of olde imagined gods of the woods, of the hils, of dales; and ſuche like innumerable: and we of late (not farre behinde) imagined eyther Angels or Saintes, beyonde the warrant of Gods worde, to flee vnto in time of neede: or when yet we imagine ſome things to be in our ſelues, or others to doo vs good, whiche in deede are not to be founde. all which things we haue to put by, and to preſſe on, to geue our ſelues wholly vnto the Lorde. The Roote is the knowledge of God; the Father, the Sonne, and the holy Ghoſt. as namely; vnder the perſon of the Father, to knowe what the Godhead is in his owne nature, not yet come foorth or vttered vnto vs. and therein more ſpecially to inquire, firſt of ſuch things as moſt properly concerne his Perſon: then of certayne other Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies that are ſomewhat farther of from the conſideration of his Perſon, or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce, and yet can neuer be ſeparated from the Godhead: laſt of all, of his will and pleaſure. Vnder the perſon of the Sonne, to knowe howe the ſelfe ſame Godhead hath declared or vttered him
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:19467:51"/> ſelfe to be knowne of others. and therein, firſte in what ſorte he beganne this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation of him ſelfe: ſecondarily, in what ſorte he dyd from time to time pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede with the ſame: thirdly, in what ſorte it muſt be accompliſhed or finiſhed. Vnder the Perſon of the holy Ghoſte to finde out in what maner the ſelfe ſame Godhead worketh in others, that he may be knowne in his demonſtration. and therein, firſte howe he worketh generally with all: and how more ſpecially he wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth with diuers kindes. firſt with the Choſen: then with Reprobates: laſt of all, with all other inferior Creatures. Out of which knowledge doth ſpring that which ſometimes is called Fayth, ſometimes Repentau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, (when we take thoſe words generally) and by diuers names beſides. which is in effect, firſt, a ſounde, &amp; a ſetled iudgement in ſuche thinges as concerne true Religion: then a feruent, and a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular loue of God, for that we finde him to be ſuche as he is: thirdly, to ſettle our ſelues wholy in him, &amp; neuer to ſeeke to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other: laſt of al, ſo obedient, ſo humble, and ſo pliable a mind, in all things to be at
<pb facs="tcp:19467:52"/> the becke of God, that putting by<note n="*" place="margin">That by theſe mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes we are ſayd to put by ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kinde on the one ſide, and all other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other ſide, that others maye bee more eaſily perſwaded therin, they muſt learne to knowe, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge of god carieth ſuch a light with it, as that thereby we doo in deede very playnely perceyue, that neither the one, nor the other of thoſe are meete to haue any ſuch honour. And firſt as touching mankinde, yf wee</note> Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde on the one ſide, and al other<note n="*" place="margin">That by theſe mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes we are ſayd to put by ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kinde on the one ſide, and all other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other ſide, that others maye bee more eaſily perſwaded therin, they muſt learne to knowe, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge of god carieth ſuch a light with it, as that thereby we doo in deede very playnely perceyue, that neither the one, nor the other of thoſe are meete to haue any ſuch honour. And firſt as touching mankinde, yf wee</note> Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures on the other, wee geue ouer our ſelues wholy to God, by a kinde of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall Homage or ſoueraigne honour. the particulars wherof doo more proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly apperteyne to the other Commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes. The grounde, or moulde where this knowledge will growe, is neuer any other, but eyther the former integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of our nature, whiche nowe is paſte our reache for euer: or els, Ieſus Chriſt, by myſticall vnion to bee incarnate with him. which way only is left vnto vs wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by wee may be able to doo any good.</p>
                  <p>ſhould giue this honour to any, it muſt nedes be, our ſelues, or others. If it be our ſelues, then is there at al no place of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, which by nature doth neuer paſſe but fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the leſſer vnto the greater. Which ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualitie is neuer found betwixt our ſelues on the one ſide, and no moe but our ſelues on the other. If it be others, then muſt it be ſuch as haue already finiſhed their race
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:19467:52"/> in this preſent world: or els thoſe that yet remayne here on the earth. If they be of the former ſorte, or haue alreadie en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded their preſente lyfe, fyrſte they are not perfect men, for that their bodies and ſoules are ſundred eche from other. ſecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darily, their bodies (a very fewe only ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted by ſpeciall prerogatiue) are yet in the bowels of the earth, not able to doe the functions of a body, but ſubiect to rottennes, and to corruption. laſte of all, their ſoules muſt needes be, eyther at reſt and bleſſed (and then exempted from the ſence &amp; knowledge of our miſerie heere) or in paynes and miſerable, and ſo, not at leyſure, nor able to geue any bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to vs. If they be ſuch as yet are on earth in this preſent worlde, eyther they are vtterly feuered from vs by diſtaunce of place (and then can they doe vs neither good nor hurte): or els they are heere a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong vs, and then are affected towards vs, eyther well and Chriſtianlyke (and then it is the worke of Gods ſpirite in them); or euill and wickedly (and then is the power of the Diuell, and their owne naughtineſſe coupled together. but
<pb facs="tcp:19467:53"/> then as they are vnwilling to do vs good, ſo are they vnable to doo vs hurt); or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differently (&amp; then neither are they of any deſertes towards vs, neither are they in dignitie but our equals, or of the ſame mould with vs.) So that whether they be ſaintes in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or damned ſoules in hel, or men liuing on earth, as they are not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to helpe or hurt vs, ſo are they neither Lords nor Ladies to vs in this accompt. Concerning other Creatures, nedes muſt they be eyther Angels of heauen; or wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſpirites, and diuels of hell; or others of theſe corruptible creatures. yf they be Angels in heauen, then are they ordeined to ſerue vs, as God from time to time ſhal imploy them: are but fellow ſeruants with vs: and haue neither authoritie ouer vs; nor any power againſt vs, or with vs. yf they be of thoſe diuels, or wicked ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites, then can they not haue but an yl wil towards vs: and yet haue they at all no power againſt vs. yf they be of other cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible creatures, either in the firmame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or elements aboue, or els on the earth, or in the waters beneath, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are they in dede the good creatures of god: ordeined to our
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:19467:53"/> vſe; but yet all our inferiors, made to doe their ſeruice to vs: otherwiſe in their owne nature but weake, and able to doe vs no pleaſure at all, but when it pleaſeth God to worke by them. So that theſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo are neither Lords nor Ladies to vs.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The ſeconde Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement.</head>
                  <p>THe ſeconde Commaundement doth ſhewe what kinde of worſhippe it muſte needes be (as touching the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce, or mater of it) wherewithall God muſte be ſerued of vs, ſo long as we lyue here in this preſent worlde. that is, To worſhippe him as he hath appointed; and none otherwiſe. But of that pece of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that goeth vnder the name of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, there be two prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall partes. the former is the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t it ſelfe: the other is the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon added in the ende, to ſtyrre vs vp to kepe this commaundement.</p>
                  <p>In the Commaundement it ſelfe we haue likewiſe to ſearch out, firſte what it
<pb facs="tcp:19467:54"/> forbiddeth: then what it requireth.</p>
                  <p>It forbiddeth, firſt as touching images a couple of Braunches: then alſo the<note n="*" place="margin">By this word roote we hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forwarde vnderſtand y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> knot or ioynt, out of which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Braunch groweth.</note> Roote of them, and whatſoeuer other Braunches come out of the ſame. The former of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> two Braunches that by name are forbidden, is to make to our ſelues, or to our vſe anie grauen image or the like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of any thing that is in heauen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue, on earth beneath, or in the waters vnder the earth (and yet not altogether; as namely, when they are but hiſtoricall &amp; ciuile: but) when they are made to ſome ſuperſtitious ende. as, eyther to expreſſe the Godheade: or, by that meanes to bring him ſomewhat nerer to vs, or to our vſe: or, to ſtirre vp, or kindle in vs any kinde of deuotion, or, as we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly ſay, to put vs in a good mynde. The other is (if it happen we haue made any ſuche, or otherwiſe light on them) to bowe downe vnto them, or to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe them. which may be done eyther for their owne ſakes; which is the groſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer error: or for others whome they are made to repreſent; which alſo is badde y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough. And we may bowe downe vnto
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:19467:54"/> them, or worſhippe them two maner of wayes. eyther by giuing ſome actuall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence vnto them; as geuing a croſſe the right hand: or, yf in fancie we make any accompt of them, or haue them in anye eſtimation. The Roote is a principall parte of infidelitie, or of the increaſe that commeth of it, which we may call a deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate or a careleſſe mind: not ſo ſoundly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting in the workes of Gods wiſedome, but that we feare the diuell will runne away with all, or at leaſt very much doubt how the matter will go, vnleſſe we adde ſomewhat more thervnto; or els haue ſo litle care of his directio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> very eaſely we go before it. The other Braunches that are in like ſorte forbidden, are many and diuers: but ſuche as may all be reduced to a couple of ſortes. For whereas our worſhippe muſte needes be eyther In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall, or els Externall, howſoeuer we ſhal happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to worſhip amiſſe, it muſt neds apperteyne to one of theſe kyndes. But wheras our Internal, or inward, or ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual worſhippe hath lykewiſe a couple of Braunches, the one of Honoure, the other of Seruice, we haue here to
<pb facs="tcp:19467:55"/> take ſo much more heede how we ſort to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether thoſe Braunches that belonge therevnto. Braunches that goe againſte his Honour, are, when we do eyther con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue any ſuch fancies or opinions as are contrary therevnto: or hauing ones con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued any ſuche, beginne to haue an eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation or a lyking of them. As for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, To thinke otherwiſe of God in any point, then he hath opened him ſelfe vnto vs: to haue other opinions in pointes of Religion, then are ſet forth in his worde: to haue other wayes to helpe our ſelues, eyther in the worke of our Redemption, in the whole, or in part; or in other things that we nede: to imagin that things come by happe or chaunce, or that ſome others beare a ſway in them; and doo not attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute al vnto god: to ſweare by any other: or ſuch lyke. Braunches that go againſte the Seruice that we owe vnto him, are lykewiſe of two ſortes. firſt when we are not in a redines to doo him ſeruice: then when we miſſe in the deede it ſelfe. Out of a redines may we put our ſelues, yf ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we hamper our ſelues vnaduiſedly, by Vowes, Mariage, Bondes, or Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice:
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:19467:55"/> or yf we doo impayre our ſelues, in Minde, Bodie, or Goodes. As touching the deede it ſelfe, that alſo is double. firſt, that whiche belongeth to our Common Calling, as we are Chriſtians: then, that which belongeth to our ſeuerall Trades, or kindes of lyfe. In the former of theſe we offende, when we eyther entre into a wrong profeſſion (as both the Iewes, &amp; Turkes doo): or when as hauing entred well, and taken vpon vs the right profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, we doe ſuche thinges as we are not charged with all. as, Superſtitious, or Pope-holy perſons vſe to do, when they do their owne, or other folkes workes: Coniurours, Exorciſtes, Witches, Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, and ſuche like when they go about without any calling to call vp, inquier of, commaunde, caſte out, bynde or hamper diuels or ſpirits; or any other ſuch feates of theirs. In the latter of theſe we offend, when as eyther we chuſe our Trade a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe; not regarding therin the calling of God, but our owne corrupt affections: or els hauing rightly choſen, do otherwiſe vnder the name of our calling, then our calling alloweth, or will beare vs out.
<pb facs="tcp:19467:56"/> Externall reſpecteth the outwarde acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Againſt it we offende, when as eyther we vſe any other rites or Ceremonies then are taught vs or warranted by the word of God (whether they be borrowed of the abrogate Leuiticall law, or deuiſed by our ſelues; or taken of others, by Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, Cuſtome, or writing) or els when we ſhrinke fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the open profeſſion of him or his truth, in worde or deede; for feare, or fauour.</p>
                  <p>It Requireth, firſt the preſent Braun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches: then alſo the Roote, and whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer other Braunches come out of the ſame. The preſent Braunches are hearte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to deteſt all ſuche images, eyther to worſhip the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; or els but to deuiſe, or make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or haue them. The Roote is, ſo fully to ſettle our ſelues in the workes of Gods wiſedome, &amp; ſo highly to eſteme of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, that neuer we go about to do any part of our owne deuiſe in thoſe matters. The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Braunches that ariſe out of the ſame, are to be taken in the ſelfe ſame order that before is ſette downe. As touching the former parte of our Inwarde wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe, whiche reſpecteth the Honour
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:19467:56"/> that we owe vnto God, firſte that we thinke or conceaue of God in euery point as he hathe opened him ſelfe vnto vs: that we conforme our opinions and iudgement in matters of Religion to the preſcript of Gods worde: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we doe ſo fully content our ſelues in him, that in all matters, as in all caſes we euer depende of, and reſt onely in him, as well for the whole worke of our Redemption, as he hath wrought it in Ieſus Chriſt; as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo for what ſoeuer els we need in this preſent worlde: that we attribute all thinges vnto God; and ſeeke vnto him in all our neceſſities: that when ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer we are iuſtly occaſioned to take an othe, then, becauſe he onely is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to witnes a truth, that wee e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer call him to witnes, and ſweare onely by him: and whatſoeuer others are of this kinde. As touching the other part, which is the Seruice that we owe vnto hym, there be two ſortes of Braunches that apperteine therevnto. the firſte, as touching our preparation to doo him Seruice: the other as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the deede it ſelfe. vnto our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration
<pb facs="tcp:19467:57"/> apperteyneth, firſt that we euer kepe in our handes all ſuche libertie and freedome as it ſhall pleaſe God to afforde vs: then that we keepe vp and mainteine our ſelues in good plight; in Minde, in Body, in Goodes, that ſo we may do our Deede the better. Vnto the Deede it ſelfe do in like ſorte apperteine two ſortes of Braunches. firſt, as touching our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Callinge, that we both carefully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue our ſelues to ſuche thinges only as ſhall be inioyned, or holde of our handes from all, tyll we are very well aſſured what is to be done: and alſo when we ſhall throughly ſee what is to be done, remoue all lets, ſet our ſelues to the dede, and continue therin. then as touching our ſeuerall Trades of lyfe, firſte that we chuſe arighte: then that faithfully we walke therin. Concerning that kinde of worſhippe that I termed Externall, and ſaide to reſpecte the outwarde action, the Braunches are, firſt that we duly vſe ſuch Sacramentes, Ceremonies, and other Exerciſes, of our faithe, as the worde of God hath commended vnto vs: and ſuch Ceremonies, and other godlie Eercices,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:19467:57"/> as ſhall from tyme to tyme be found mete for vs, and rightly by thoſe that are in authoritie commended vnto vs. then al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that we euer profeſſe our faith in this naughtie worlde, in worde and deede, as occaſion ſhall at any tyme ſerue.</p>
                  <p>As touching the reaſon that he addeth in the ende, to ſtyrre vs vp to keepe this Commaundement, it is double. For firſt he denounceth his iudgements againſte thoſe that breake it: and then vnfouldeth his mercie towards them that obſerue it.</p>
                  <p>In the denuntiation of his Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes there are diuers thinges to be conſidered. Firſt that he is <hi>The Lord our God:</hi> and therefore ought to be had in ſo muche reuerence, as the keeping of this commaundement requireth. Then that he is Ielouſe and therefore can not abide, that we ſhould turne to the deuiſes of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Thirdly that he viſiteth the <hi>Sinnes of the fathers vppon their children,</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the third and fourth generation. wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he geueth vs to vnderſtand, not, what he euer doth: but in what caſe ſuche doe ſtand in reſpect of their owne reprobate wayes. That is, that Idolatrous pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes,
<pb facs="tcp:19467:58"/> are in manifeſt daunger to haue, both their idolatrie &amp; ſuperſtition caſt on their children (and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe children nede not ſo much to triumph or glory to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue ſo obſtinate in their fathers wayes: but rather acknowledge it to be the hande of God, and his feareful vengeaunce, that they haue no better grace. which alſo is not the leaſt cauſe, that this preſent gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of ours, deſcended for the moſt part of Popiſh parents, is yet ſo froward as it is): And their other ſinnes likewiſe ſo caſt vpon them, that for their ſakes they ſhall be eyther accurſed clene, or much pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, and diuerſly plagued; though not in ſuch ſort, but that their owne deſertes ſhall alſo require it together with the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Laſt of all, that he termeth them, that hauing Images and ſuch other toyes breake this commaundement, no one iote better then <hi>Haters of him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Hauing ſo denounced, then he ſtrecheth out his armes of mercy to imbrace all thoſe, euen vnto thouſands, that geue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues to obſerue this commaundement. wherin are three principall things to bee conſidered. Firſt, that he will be <hi>merciful
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:19467:58"/> to them.</hi> Secondarily, that howſoeuer the fooliſhe and frantike worlde accompt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe of them, that abhorre to geue godly honour to Saincts &amp; Images; or, in their owne deuiſes to be as ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous as they: yet God him ſelfe termeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <hi>Louers of him.</hi> Thirdly, that he cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleth together theſe two thinges, to loue God, and to keepe his commaundemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. by occaſion whereof we may learne this one thing, that neyther can we be founde to loue him, vnleſſe we endeuour our ſelues to keepe his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes (a ready barre for all hypocrites) neither can we kepe his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes, vnles we loue him (that al Image-worſhippers may ſee them ſelues playnly excluded).</p>
                  <p>Let Popery beware, that it neuer come to be examined by this commaundement. It is no maruell, that they would ſo glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly haue ſtollen it out.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The thirde Commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement.</head>
                  <p>THe third doth teach vs, that we ſhould inwardly haue ſo notable a reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
<pb facs="tcp:19467:59"/> of God, as that this worſhippe be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore deſcribed ſhoulde euer be pouldre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> with true ſincerity. And it hath two prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall partes. firſt the Commaundemen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> it ſelfe: then the threatning that is added therevnto.</p>
                  <p>In the Commaundement it ſelfe w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> haue to conſider, firſt what it forbiddeth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> then what it requireth.</p>
                  <p>It forbiddeth, firſt one Braunch: the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Roote, &amp; whatſoeuer other Braun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches come out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame. The Braunch is<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to take y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of the Lord our god ydly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or in vaine. eyther by ſwearing ydly by him; or howſoeuer els we talke of him a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> a venture, or to no purpoſe. The Roote is Vnreuerencie towardes God. The other Braunches that come out of this Roote are many of them as had as this, &amp; ſome much worſe, and all together very many in nombre: but ſuch as may very well be reduced to a couple of ſortes. whereof the former is of thoſe wherby we breake this Commaundement as we are Chriſtians, or in reſpect of our common Calling. the other of thoſe wereby it is broken in cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of our particular Callings or Trades
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:19467:59"/> of lyfe. Of the firſte ſorte are, firſt Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie: that is, vnder the name of Gods ſeruaunt, eyther not to receaue Chriſtian Religion, in the whole, or in ſome mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall pointe: or not to haue it our ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to lyue accordingly. eyther in the whole, or in ſome parte. Secondarily in ſwearing, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſweare either by God, either contrary to our knowledge, falſly; or whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we know it not certainly to be as we ſay; or but vainely, when there is no vrgent neceſſitie: or by the Manhodde of Chriſte, or ſome part thereof, eyther cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly and outragiouſly; or in ſuch ſorte as before is ſet downe of God: or by any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Thirdly in our Publique Seruice, yf eyther thoſe to whome the adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof is committed, behaue them ſelues vnreuerently, or otherwiſe then becommeth them that in theſe thinges re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent the perſon of God, eyther in the worde; or in the Sacraments; or in their Diſcipline or ſpirituall Cenſure; or in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Eccleſiaſticall functions: or ſuche as are partakers therof, eyther receaue them; or behaue them ſelues there in, otherwiſe then they ought to doe, or as becommeth
<pb facs="tcp:19467:60"/> thoſe that are before the eyes of God. Fourthly, yf at any other tyme we a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe<note n="*" place="margin">As it is the maner, firſt of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times wre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting the ſcriptures to a wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, or a tri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fling ſenſe, ſometymes iangling or ieſting of them, and other holy miſteries. then alſo of Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iurers, witches, Sorcerers and Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing (or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſing ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) thoſe holy thynges in their wicked and dyueliſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> doinges. laſt of all of Papiſtes in many of their doinges: a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſing the Scriptures very muche, applying the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes after the ſame maner, as Baptiſme to bels, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Lordes Supper to deade men, and halowing of deade ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to their trifling, or wicked purpoſes.</note> holy thinges: as the Scripture, or any parcell thereof; eyther of the two Sacramentes; good prayers; or bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings; the name of God; Hallowinges alſo; or ſuch lyke.</p>
                  <p>Laſte of all when we counterfete, or take to our vſe, or make common ſuche<note n="*" place="margin">As the miraculous faſt of Chriſt: Spitle: Ephata: ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme vnction: Sacrificers: Maſſe-geſtures. &amp;c.</note> extraordinarie miracles or other excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies as it hath pleaſed the Godheade to ſhewe foorth eyther in Chriſte or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wayes, not to our imitation, but to the beautifying of him ſelfe, or his worde. Of the other ſorte are diuers; but ſuche as doe apperteine vnto thoſe that are, eyther in authoritie, or dignitie ouer others: and in that reſpecte repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent vnto others the perſon of God. Of the former are Princes, vnder-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:19467:60"/> Miniſters, Parentes, Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandes, Scholemaſters, and Maſters of howſhouldes: and whoſoeuer els haue any authoritie ouer others. The Braun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches that do apperteine to thoſe, are, firſt as touching their lyfe and conuerſation, yf they do not their endeuour, euen in their Perſons to repreſent the holynes; and the reuerende maieſtie of God. Then as touching the maner of their gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or ordering of thoſe that are vnder their charge, firſt yf they will rule by will without any lawes: ſecondarily yf their lawes be yll: thirdly, yf, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their lawes are good, they do not execute y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame. Their lawes may be yl, &amp; vnmete for the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſeat of god, yf either they tend not to that ende, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god hath preſcribed: or doe it not with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame equabilitie or moderatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Thende whervnto their lawes &amp; orders muſt tend is double. firſt to make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euer more &amp; more y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> citize<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s or ſubiects of gods kingdome, in religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; vertuous life: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they liue an orderly, peaceable, &amp; proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous life one with an other. The modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of faults, they be nei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther more rigorous, nor remiſſe: in rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb facs="tcp:19467:61"/> of well-doing, neither more harde, nor liberall, then God, hath preſcribed by the directio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his word. Their execution will likewiſe be faultie, yf eyther they pardon in the whole, or in parte, ſuche as are in falne within the ſenſe and meaning of the lawe: or puniſh thoſe in the whole, or in parte, that are not founde to haue tranſgreſſed. Of the latter, that is of thoſe that are but in Dignitie preferred before others, are the more learned, the more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, the more noble, the more cunning, &amp; the richer ſort. The Braunch that apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teineth to theſe, is no more but this, yf they walke not before God and men in ſuch ſorte, as becommeth thoſe whome it hath pleaſed God to cloth with ſo hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable garments before many others; and to chuſe them from among the reſte, to beare his treaſures and precious iewels.</p>
                  <p>It requireth, firſt the contrary Braunch: then alſo the Roote it ſelfe, and, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer other Braunches come out of the ſame. The Braunch is, whenſoeuer we talke of god, to do it with reuerence. The Roote is a ſingular Reuerence of God. The Braunches that apperteine herevn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:19467:61"/> by vertue of our common Calling, are, firſt as touching our profeſſion to receaue Chriſtian Religion in euery pointe: and vnfeinedly to endeuour our ſelues to liue accordingly in all thinges. As for ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, firſte, that whenſoeuer we ſweare we euer ſweare by our holy God: then alſo in ſuch ſorte as we ought to do. firſte ſo truly, that there be in our oth, not only no plaine falſhoode; but alſo no maner of diſſimulation: then alſo, that we do not ſweare ſo neyther, but when we are by good occaſion vrged thervnto. As touching our diuine ſeruice, that ſuche as miniſter, do ſo behaue them ſelues, as beſt may ſhew forth, howe holy thoſe thinges are; and the very truth, and maieſtie of them: that ſuch as be partakers of them, receaue them as at the hands of God; and behaue them ſelues as in his preſence. As touching thoſe other holy things, that we haue ſuch an eſtimatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the holines and maieſtie of God, that we abhorre more then a thouſande deathes, to vſe his moſt bleſſed name, his Scriptures his Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, or good prayers which ſhoulde alſo be his, but to moſte holy and godly
<pb facs="tcp:19467:62"/> vſes, ſuch as him ſelfe hath ordeined them for. Laſt of all, that in no wiſe we drawe to our imitation any ſuch excellencies as we finde done to his owne glory, or the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendation of his honour: but that with reuerence we ſet them by, and leaue them wholly vnto him ſelfe. The Braunches that do apperteine herevnto by vertue of thoſe ſeuerall eſtates, are, firſt for thoſe that are in authority, that firſt as touching their conuerſation among men, that they ſo behaue them ſelues, as may reſemble, ſo neere as they can, both the holynes and maieſtie of God: then as touching the forme of their gouernement, that their Lawes be good, as well in ende, as mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration; that they gouerne by the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript therof; and euer put them in dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent execution. Then as touching them that are in dignitie before others, that they walke in ſuche ſorte as becommeth thoſe whom God hath honoured, and choſen to carie ſo precious things.</p>
                  <p>In the Threatning annexed therevnto, we haue to beholde, that howſoeuer we may accompte it but a ſmall matter ſo lightly to take into oure mouthes the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:19467:62"/> name of our moſte holye God: yet the Lorde, in his Iuſtice, findeth it to be ſo great a ſinne, as that he muſt needes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne for it. And then doth there an heauie iudgement remayne for thoſe that are the worſt ſort of this kinde of ſinners.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement.</head>
                  <p>THe fourth Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement requireth that we walke thoſe wayes that it hath pleaſed God to lay foorth to bring vs to this worſhippe before deſcribed. But the peece of Scripture that belongeth thervnto, may be diuided into three prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall partes. The firſt to be the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement it ſelfe, of the ſeuenth dayes reſt: the ſeconde, the conceſſion or allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce of ſixe dayes working: the thirde and laſt, by what reaſon he perſwadeth vs to keepe this reſt.</p>
                  <p>As touching the commaundemet it ſelfe we haue to conſider, ſomewhat otherwiſe then in the others, firſt what it requireth: then what it forbiddeth.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19467:63"/>
                  <p>It requireth firſt one Braunch y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> here is named: then alſo the Roote, and whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer other Braunches come oute of the ſame. The Braunch is no more but this, that we keepe<note n="*" place="margin">As tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching this firſt &amp; principal Braunch it is to be conſidered, that firſte as touching the preciſe neceſſitie for the outward obſeruation thereof, which was caſt vppon the Iſraelites tyll the comming of Chriſte, that is not ſo layd vpon vs, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we may very well imploy that day alſo to our v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall labour, yf at any tyme the rule of charitie or Chriſtian dutie ſhall ſo requyer, vppon ſome extraordinarie occaſion. Then as touching a certen free obſeruation of it, that it doth yet remaine in force with vs. The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that are commonly geuen are theſe. Firſte to expreſſe the ſpirituall reſt that we haue in Chriſt. Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning which, it is very true that we haue a notable reſte in him. Neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe to keepe the Sabboth to that ende, dyd apperteine to the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites alone tyll Chriſte came in the fleſhe: not vnto vs, nor to them ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſith nowe he is come, and how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer the Iewes can not yet leaue their ſuperſtition therein: yet full li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle doth it become Chriſtians, being now paſt children, ſtill notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to go by the wall. Secondarily to make the eſtate of ſeruaunts and cattle, that are vnder worldly Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, more tolerable. Concerning which it ſeemeth rather to be an accidentall comoditie, that the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sabbath bringeth with it: then an eſſentiall purpoſe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto it was ordeyned: although in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eternall Reſt of ours, not onely ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes, but all other creatures ſhall likewiſe haue reſt. Neuertheleſſe, ſeeing that God him ſelfe did often point the Iſraelites therevnto, he is not I warrant you any Chriſtian, that hath not a iuſte conſideration of it alſo: partly for that he hath not that moderation: but ſpecally becauſe that ſo he keepeth his ſeruauntes, from the meanes of their ſaluation. The thirde and the principall reaſon is, that it may ſerue our nedefull vſe: that both by the godly exerciſe that we haue in our publique aſſemblies, and by our priuate meditation, God may in dede work our ſanctification and ſoperforme the thing that we ſeeke. Beſides theſe reaſons, which are by others commonly geuen, the Scripture noteth one other, which is that the Sabbath day ſhould be a token vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that (not they them ſelues or any other, but) the Lorde onely wrought their ſanctification. to which ende, although that we are not bound to obſerue it, becauſe that ſo taken it is a figure abrogate: yet may we ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly gather out of it theſe two points that we alſo are ſantified by no other meanes: &amp; that it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh vs plainely to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge it, &amp; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to kepe it in freſhe remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce.</note> holy the ſeuenth day, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting from our v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual labours ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. The Roote is, to be godly min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; or, to haue an vnfeined, and an earneſte deſire to attayne to thys worſhippe before deſcribed; and ſo throughly to be ſanctified by the gracious woorke of God in vs, that euery day more &amp; more wee maye ceaſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our owne naturall woorkes whiche euer are naught, and be oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupied in his, that ſo we may wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:19467:63"/> him aright. The other Braun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches that do grow out of his Roote, are many and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers. Firſte, ſuche as doe apperteine to the keping holy or right vſe of the Sabboth day, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that other whiche is already ſette downe. as namely, to ſpende the whole Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both day, eyther in Publique exerciſe, as in ordinary ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, or Sermons: or in priuate me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditaio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, examining in what caſe we are, and lifting vp our heartes vnto God in thankes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geuing, or prayer as occaſion is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered;
<pb facs="tcp:19467:64"/> and preſcribing to our ſelues whatſoeuer is of vs to be done. or in ſuch other workes of charitie, as by iuſte occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion we ſhall be at any time called vnto. Then alſo whereas it is knowne well inough, that God worketh that worſhip afore ſaide in vs by ſecondary cauſes, we may oute of it eaſely gather, that by the vertue of this commaundement we are led to ſeeke out the benefite of them, and to take it vnto our ſelues. Of theſe ſecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darie cauſes I find two ſorts. wherof the former may well be termed Ordinarie meanes wherby it pleaſeth god to worke: the other are more properly Helpes, for the better working of thoſe meanes. So, theſe other Braunches, which do apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to this Com. may well be reduced vnto a couple of principall ſortes. the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer of thoſe that doe apperteine to theſe Ordinarie meanes: the latter of thoſe that do apperteine to thoſe other Helpes.</p>
                  <p>As touching both which there are three principall thinges that in this place were to be conſidred. firſt what they are: ſecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darily how God worketh by them: third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in what ſort we haue to meete with the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:19467:64"/> working of God, or howe to take the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite of them. But becauſe the firſte &amp; the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of theſe three are alreadie ſet downe in the former booke wherevnto they do more properly apperteine, here we ſhall nede to talke but of the third, that is, how we ought to take the benefite of them.</p>
                  <p>Therefore to come to thoſe Ordinarie meanes, the word, the Sacramentes, the Church, &amp; Gouernment, this is our duty in euery one. Firſt, as touching the worde we ought ſo highly to eſteeme of it, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> not only we ſtudy it by our ſelues; &amp; dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly geue eare to the ſame being read vnto vs: but alſo, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we euer mainteine y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miniſtery, ſo far as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> direction of God doth lead vs. The myſterie of the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts haue we often to vnfolde before our eies, euer ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing therby to mainteine &amp; better our v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with Chriſt: and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenting our ſelues, once to haue receiued thone; ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to quicke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp our faith by thother. As touching the Church we muſt in dede be one of them: &amp; yet we muſte take good hede vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. As touchinge the former of theſe two pointes, becauſe they are the people of God, we haue to aſſociate our ſelues vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them; and among them, ſo nere as we
<pb facs="tcp:19467:65"/> can (not diuiding our ſelues fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the reſt) to the better ſort: when once we are come together, not to part againe without iuſt occaſion; nor to geue them occaſion to caſt vs out; or to ſunder themſelues from vs: but euer keeping with them, diligently to reape from tyme to tyme, whatſoeuer ſpirituall commoditie we may haue by them. As touching the latter, becauſe they are but Men, we muſte beware, leaſte yf they happen to fall from the truth, eyther in the whole as the Iewes, and Turkes; or but in part, as the church of Rome ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fouly hath don, they cary vs alſo with them. Laſte of all, that we may reape the benefite of Gouernement, firſte we haue to ſubmit our ſelues willingly to drawe in the yoke thereof: not onely when our Magiſtrates them ſelues are good; and their lawes very eaſie: but alſo when the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues are bad &amp; tyrannous; &amp; their lawes very greuous. ſo long as the greuouſnes of them conſiſteth, not in commaunding ſuch thinges as are yll; nor in forbidding ſuch things as are good eyther in nature, or in circumſtance as the caſe ſtandeth: but onely in reſtreining our outwarde
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:19467:65"/> liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, in thinges indifferent. Then al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo we muſte doo our endeuour to maine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine and vpholde them with our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, Prayer, Bodie, &amp; Goodes: whether them ſelues be good or badde; ſo long as they are our lawfull Magiſtrates.</p>
                  <p>The Helpes that I ſpeake of, which it hath pleaſed the wiſedome of God to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend vnto vs for our better furtherance in thoſe meanes (and therefore to be ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with them) are theſe three: watching, Faſting, and Prayer. Concerning which, we haue in like ſorte, but the thirde point to conſider. that is, howe we ſhould helpe our ſelues by theſe which euery one may ſee to be this. that we ought diligently to occupie our ſelues therein, in them all, &amp; in euery of them. or in a fewe moe words, firſte that we aduiſe our ſelues with all poſſible circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpection, what it is we haue to doe: what may hinder, or further the ſame. Secondarily that we be ſo earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ben to do what we ſhould, that we bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily auoide whatſoeuer may turne vs out of the way, or but hinder vs therein: and redily vſe whatſoeuer may ſet vs through the way, or neuer ſo little helpe vs for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde.
<pb facs="tcp:19467:66"/> Laſt of all that we haue ſo liuely a feeling of our owne wretchednes and weakenes on the one ſide, and of the abu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunce and gracious kindnes that is in God on the other ſide, that to the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunce of theſe things, we ſeke vnto god with feruencie of minde. and, to the ende that our prayers may better ſpeede, we e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer purge our ſelues from our ſinne, leaſt that by the reaſon of it we become odious vnto him: and neuer freight our heads ſo full of worldly fancies, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we may be able to kepe our minds vnto our praiers.</p>
                  <p>It forbiddeth, firſt the Braunch: then al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the Roote, &amp; whatſoeuer other Braun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches come out of the ſame. The Braunch is, to be occupied in our vſual affayres on the Sabboth day. The Roote is, to be worldly minded: or, to haue ſo litle acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt of our inwarde ſanctification, that we do not much care though ſtill we remaine as bad as before, and euer be occupied in the workes of our owne corrupt nature. The other Braunches y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> do ſpring out of the ſame are diuers. Firſt ſuch as do ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perteine to the Sabboth day it ſelfe, if we beſtowe it, or any parte of it in ydlenes,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:19467:66"/> goodfelowſhippe, inordinate feaſtinge, drinking, gamning, or ſuch like: or yf we abſent our ſelues from the ordinarie Diuine Seruice: or yf we either cauſe, or ſuffer others that are vnder our charge, ſo to doo. Secondarily, as touching thoſe Ordinarie meanes before ſette downe, yf we haue ſo litle care to be godly, that we behaue our ſelues cleane contrarie to that whiche is before ſette downe. As namely, firſte as touching the worde, yf eyther we doo flatly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe and abhorre; or els not ſingular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly regarde, eyther the reading or the hearing of it: or if eyther wee doo cleane plucke downe the Miniſterie; or by our niggardly allowaunce, but ſteale away the force thereof. as for the Sacramentes, yf eyther altogether we ſhunne them: or but in ſome poyntes after our manner abuſe them: buryinge the one in deepe obliuyon: and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to the other, eyther vnreuerently; or very ſeldome; or not at all, but for feare of cyuile coercion, or ſhame of the worlde. Concerninge the Church, or in it the better ſorte, yf eyther we neuer
<pb facs="tcp:19467:67"/> ioyne vnto them; or quickly ſtart out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine; or make them weary of our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany; or take not to vs the benefite of them. And as for Gouernement, yf we be ſo much geuen to lyue after our licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious will, that eyther we go about to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow it one way or other; or els lyue not by the rule of it, at leaſt whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we hope that we are in ſecrete. Laſt of all as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching thoſe Helpes, yf we doo not vſe them as is deſcribed. Firſte concerning watching, yf eyther we do not aduice our ſelues of thoſe thinges aforeſaide: or, yf they happen to come into our heades, forthwith ſuppreſſe them, and lull our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues a ſleepe in ſecuritie againe. As for fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, if we vſe not occaſions of goodnes; nor auoide occaſions of naughtines: but tenderly ſpare our labour in the one, and licentiouſly geue ouer our ſelues to the other: and in the meane ſeaſon ſet downe our ſelues in ſome wicked, or vaine toy in the name of Faſting. Laſt of all as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching Prayer, the Braunches are, eyther neuer to trouble our ſelues therewith, eyther not at all, or not in our owne per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; but to put ouer that charge vnto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers:
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:19467:67"/> or els, yf our ſelues will take a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle paynes ſometimes therin, to be ſure of this, that eyther we ſlippe a ſide from God, and ſteale to ſome Saint; or haue our prayers in a tongue that we doe not vnderſtande; or make but a lip-labour of them, putting our heart and minde to other vſes, and leauing our lippes and fingers ends only to them.</p>
                  <p>The Conceſſion or graunting of ſixe dayes labour is nowe to be ſene. Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning which we haue to conſider, firſt that it is no parte of the Commaundement it ſelfe (ſpeaking properly) but onely a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, or an allowance: Secondarily that ſeeing it is ſo liberall allowaunce as it is, it ought to perſwade vs, in no wiſe to medle with the ſeuenth day to any ſuch vſe. Thirdly that it is not ſo to be taken, but that we may haue other holy dayes beſides (as they may be vſed) notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding this: the nature of an allowau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch, as that it ſtandeth of force but ſo farre, as it is not reſtrained by ſome other law of as great authoritie. Laſt of all, that ſeing God chargeth vs with<note n="*" place="margin">For as for thoſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther feaſtes that were appointed to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme, (whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>h di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters, not ſufficiently aduiſed of the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall ende or vſe of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, allotted vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t) they ſtoode for their tyme by vertue of the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, &amp; not by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of this for euer: &amp; ſo are now aboliſhed with other ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies.</note> no moe, it may ſeeme not to be ſo very needefull to haue any moe but only this.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19467:68"/>
                  <p>Concerning the laſt part, which is the reaſon whervpon the obſeruation of this Com. is grounded, the ſame is double. The firſt reaſon is, becauſe god him ſelf, hauing finiſhed his worke in thoſe ſixe dayes that went before, did reſt the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth. Which ſeemeth to conclude two things. The firſte very plaine: that ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he hath geuen vs example to doo that, wherevnto his worde doeth direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly call vs, we as naturall children ought in this point to follow our fathers exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. The other more darke, and more vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certen in it ſelfe: neuertheleſſe ſo well holpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> otherwayes, that it alſo may come before our eyes. whiche is no more but this: that yf as the world was made in ſix dayes, and the ſeuenth was a day of reſt, ſo is it likely to ſtand towards the point of ſix thouſand yeres, &amp; then immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the eternall reſte in glorie to beginne (which not onely diuers of the learned haue ſaid, &amp; great likelihoods do import: but alſo the ſcriptures do ſeme to witnes both by the whole and vniuerſall courſe of them, and alſo by certaine particular places) then may a man in the ſeuenth
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:19467:68"/> dayes reſte more ſenſiblie perceaue, that nowe our Redemption, to ſo many as labour, is nere at hande: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that it is tyme to lyft vppe our heades, both becauſe wee are alreadie come to the ſixte dayes afternoone; and hope that of thoſe yeares which yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine, a good nombre ſhall be cut off. Inſomuch that hence ariſeth double in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. firſte to thoſe that will not ceaſſe from their owne workes here, that they muſte in the worlde to come la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in eternall tormentes: ſo that they can not with any ſounde comforte be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde the Seuenth dayes reſte, then that thoſe that heere ceaſſe from their owne workes, that they ſhall reſt in the world to come: ſo that they may moſt ioyfully beholde the Seuenth dayes reſt, that is vnto them ſo comfortable a meſſenger, of ſo bleſſed an eſtate, ſo neere at hande. The other reaſon is, for that God bleſſed the Seuenth day, &amp; hallowed it. which alſo geueth double inſtruction. Firſte that ſuche as truly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour them ſelues to obſerue this Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth dayes reſt in ſuche ſort as is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed,
<pb facs="tcp:19467:69"/> ſhall no doubt become godlie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God hath bleſſed it to that ende: then alſo that it is no maruell, that ſuche as ſo litle accompt as they do, to obſerue it as they ought to do, are ſo vngodly and wicked as they are; becauſe they refuſe this bleſſing of God that ſhoulde make them better.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The fift Commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement.</head>
                  <p>THe fift Commaundement teacheth vs to linke together one with an other in ſuch order as we find that God him ſelfe from tyme to tyme doth ſette among vs. For ſeeing that it requireth, that all infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iors honour their ſuperiors, or ſubmitte themſelues vnto them, and all are inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors in ſome reſpect, euen the higheſt of al: we may boldly conclude, that this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement knitteth vs all together in one, and ſo layeth the very foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (nexte after our dutie to Gods owne Perſon) of euery State or common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth. And in deede, there is nothing
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:19467:69"/> that ſo knitteth together, as for to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge this ſubiection, and gladly to honour and reuerence eche other. But of this Commaundement there are likewiſe two principall partes. firſt the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement it ſelfe: then the promiſe annexed therevnto.</p>
                  <p>In the Commaundement it ſelfe wee haue to conſider, firſt what it requireth: then what it forbiddeth.</p>
                  <p>It requireth firſt the Braunch; then al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the Roote, and whatſoeuer other brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches come out of the ſame. The Braunch of whiche firſt it ſpeaketh, is, to honour our naturall parentes. The Roote out of which this Braunche doth growe, is a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, and a diligent conſideration, howe good things it hath pleaſed God to geue forth in the world to our vſe: and namely (ſo much as apperteineth to this preſent Braunche) howe great good thinges he hath beſtowed on vs by our naturall<note n="*" place="margin">The good things that by them he beſtoweth on vs, are, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times good education, lands, and goodes: if none of thoſe, yet perhappes a good wyl to haue done al theſe things for vs, &amp; a natural loue continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing towards vs. yf not thys neither, yet, at leaſt, that by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we liue. Which is, both in it ſelfe a precious thing: &amp; to the faythfull, an earneſt of a better eſtate, &amp; away or paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage vnto the ſame. So com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth it to paſſe, that althogh we neuer receiued any thing els of our Parentes, though they were the worſt, and the moſt vnnaturall that euer li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: yet euen for this onely ought they to be had in ſpeciall honour. and that, not onely of thoſe that finde them ſelues to be ſealed to that better e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate in the world to come: but alſo of thoſe that yet perceiue no ſuch thing in them ſelues. becauſe that eyther hereafter they may: or els if neuer they come to that prerogatiue, yet had they as muche of their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes as others.</note> Parentes. The other Braunches that come out of this Roote, are, in like maner to honour all others to whom we find our ſelues to be bound for the like
<pb facs="tcp:19467:70"/> good thinges: wherewith it hath pleaſed god to our vſe to furniſhe them, and therein to make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect our parents. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there are very many that by this accompt muſt be had in reuerence of vs (though not all alike) it ſhal be nedefull, firſt to ſee who they are: and then what kinde of honour ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perteineth to euery of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Beginning therefore to ſearch out who they are, whom it hath pleaſed god in this reſpect to make our Parents, heere muſte wee needes beginne with the<note n="*" place="margin">Heere is to be noted that both in the Trees, and in the Braunches that belong to this Commaundement, the firſt diuiſion (whiche is into fiue partes) repreſenteth the perſons to whom this honor is due: all the reſt that ſpring out of the ſame, the honour that is due vnto them.</note> man Ieſus Chriſte. in whom it hath pleaſed the Godheade, that all ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſhoulde dwell; and that in him ſhoulde bee layde vp for vs all the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtimable
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:19467:70"/> treaſures of Gods gooodnes. that as he ſhould be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> head of his Church, and therefore the very foundation, or the corner ſtone of our mutuall Societie one with an other: ſo might we finde in him, that which might ſufficiently commende him vnto vs in that reſpect, and haue him fuly furniſhed therevnto. From Chriſte deſcending to men on earth wee finde of them two ſortes. firſt, thoſe vnto whom we are ſpecially bounde: then all others. we are ſpecially bounde vnto three ſorts, firſte to thoſe that are in authoritie ouer vs: as Parentes, Princes, vnder-magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, ſpirituall Paſtors and Maſters. Secondarily, to thoſe that are in dignitie preferred before vs: as (beſides thoſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore rehearſed) the Learned, the aged, the honorable or worſhipfull, the Riche, and thoſe that are ſkilfull or cunning in their Sciences or Trades of life. Thirdly, to thoſe that haue a care of vs, or beare good will vnto vs: as kinſfolke, neighbours, and all other freendes. All others like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe come vnder this accompte, for that they are, or at leaſt may be (for ought that we knowe) euen the fartheſt and meaneſt
<pb facs="tcp:19467:71"/> of all, to very great vſe vnto vs. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, hauing ſo taken in all liuing men, we haue yet to ſtretch forth this conſideration to many others: Angels; dead men; and other Creatures. Firſt, as touching An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, they are to be taken into this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt, for that it pleaſeth God to vſe their miniſterie or ſeruice to our vſe heere in this world. Of dead men that belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto, there are two ſortes. the former is of thoſe that perhaps are departed long ſince, and yet haue ſo beſtowed their time while they liued, that they are in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce with vs; for that they haue ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunced the Goſpell, or the knowledge and fayth of Chriſt, eyther by their lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, or by their life, or by their death: or els ſome other way haue done good to their poſteritie in earthly matters. the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is of thoſe our kinſfolke, neighbours or frends that are newly departed. Thoſe other creatures that belong herevnto, are all theſe, whereby it pleaſeth God in any reſpect to doo good vnto vs.</p>
                  <p>As touching the Honour that appertei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to theſe, the ſame is not alike vnto al. But whatſoeuer it is, it apperteyneth to
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:19467:71"/> one of theſe three Braunches; Obedience, Mainteinaunce, or Reuerence. Vnto Chriſt Ieſus are they all due: obedience vnto his worde; mainteinaunce to his cauſe; and to his members on earth; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence to him, and all his, and that ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely, or without exception; and moſt fully, or after the largeſt manner. Vnto thoſe that are in authoritie ouer vs are they likewiſe all due; but with limitation. For firſt as touching obedience, it is due vnto them ſo farre as they doo not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde any thing contrarie to the worde of God, eyther in it ſelfe; or as the caſe ſtandeth in other reſpectes. As for main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teinaunce by body or goodes, if they bee publique perſons, or haue in hande the gouernement of the State, then haue we to yeelde what they charge vs withall to the vttermoſt penie of our abilitie, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out<note n="*" place="margin">Firſt, for that they are Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and demaunde it to our common vſe, or for the mainteinaunce of the whole: then al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo for that we beeing but priuate men, and knowing no more but ſome part, can not be competent Iudges of the whole, whereof we are ignoraunt.</note> diſcuſſing whether they take to much or not. If they be but Priuate men (as ſpiritual paſtors, Parents, and Maſters) then may we vſe our own diſcretion ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in:
<pb facs="tcp:19467:72"/> but yet mainteine them to our power ſo long as we ſee, firſt on their parts, that they doo in deede neede it to good, &amp; nede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vſes: then on ours, that we are able to performe it, both in reſpect of our ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; &amp; in reſpect of our eſtate, or vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> buſines that we haue otherwiſe to do. Reuerence is due to them all: but, degrees to be vſed therin; and none to be reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced aboue meaſure, as though they were ſome certaine gods, or nere thervn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. Vnto thoſe that are but in dignitie preferred before vs, nothing peculiarly to them in that reſpect, but only reuerence is due: that is, to make that accompt of them inwardly; and outwardly to haue them in that eſtimation that belongeth vnto them. Vnto thoſe that beare vs good will theſe poyntes of Reuerence; duly to eſteeme of their good will: and to haue the like in ſtore for them agayne. Vnto al others, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence likewiſe, or ſo highly to eſteme of them, as that we make no other accompte of any, then as of notable veſſels of the treaſures of god. and this, although they be vnknowne to vs; or ſeme to haue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at al in them; or be maliciouſly bent
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:19467:72"/> agaynſt vs. Vnto Angels likewiſe, vnto the dead, &amp; to other Creatures, a certayne kinde of Reuerence likewiſe, and nothing els. As namely, that we eſteeme of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, as of the excellent creatures of God, ordeined to our vſe, and doing their office accordingly: and if we haue any ſet me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (for edifying, without ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion appoynted vnto vs) to performe the ſame with due Reuerence. As touching thoſe of the dead long ſince that haue giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d teſtimonie of their fayth, and are at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned to their triumph in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that we haue them in reuerende and thankfull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce, whether it be for their wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, or liues, or deathes: as at all times els; ſo eſpecially when we haue any ſet memoriall of them, to prouoke vs to bee thankfull to God on their behalfe, or our ſelues to folow their vertuous examples: as for the others by whom we receiue but ſome earthly bleſſing, yet to haue them alſo in their degree in very reuerende and thankefull remembraunce. As for thoſe that are newly departed, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we bring them ſemely vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ground; kepe vp their good name ſo well as we may; and doo
<pb facs="tcp:19467:73"/> for thoſe that are lefte behinde them. As for all inferior Creatures, that we haue them alſo in that accompt, that we allowe them that place and eſtate that God hath geuen them; and that whenſoeuer we haue occaſion to vſe them, we doo it with ſobrietie and reuerence.</p>
                  <p>It forbiddeth, firſt the Braunche: then alſo the Roote, and whatſoeuer other Braunches come oute of the ſame. The Braunche is to diſhonour our naturall Parents. The Roote is to drowne or ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thoſe good things that it hath pleaſed god to lay vp in others to our vſe: as though eyther there were no ſuche in them; or otherwiſe that wee could doo wel inough without them. The other Braunches that come out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, are many and diuers. Firſt of all, as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching Chriſte, the Father of our eternall brotherhoode, eyther not all to yeelde him thoſe poyntes of honour; or not ſo fully as we ought to doo. As touching thoſe two ſortes of men, and firſt of all them to whome we are more ſpecially bounde, and among them, thoſe that are in authoritie ouer vs, eyther to diſobey
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:19467:73"/> them in ſuch thinges as in which they go not againſt the worde of God, eyther o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly; or couertly: or to depoſe their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; mainteine or ſet vp an other againſt them, or ouer them; or to denie them ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficent maintenaunce of our gooddes or landes: or but to haue them in any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt; or not ſo great reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce as is due vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in thought, word, or deede. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condarily as touching thoſe that are but in dignity before vs, either in heart, or els by ſome open fact altogether to diſeſteme or deſpiſe them: or not to acknowledge them ſuch as they are, but to diminiſh or kepe in ſome part of their due eſtimatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Thirdly as touching thoſe others y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> beare vs good will, eyther to make but ſmall acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt of their good will: or to ſhew our ſelues vnthankfull when occaſion is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered. Then as touching all others, yf by a wicked preiudice or ſecretely with our ſelues we condemne any, eyther for very yll perſons; or but to be to litle purpoſe or els in outward appearaunce ſhewe our ſelues to haue them in that accompt. Laſt of all as touching Angels, dead men, and inferior Creatures, yf we haue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not in
<pb facs="tcp:19467:74"/> that reuerence euery ſorte in their degree as we ought to haue. As for Angels, yf we haue them in any contempt: or yf vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reuerently we ſolemnize ſuch good me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morials as we haue or may haue of them. As for Saintes, or thoſe deade men that haue lefte notable monumentes of their faith behinde them, yf lykewiſe we diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſteme eyther them ſelues, or their good thinges that they haue left vnto vs, defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing their writings, their doings, or their monume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, being other wiſe good or al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowable ynough: or yf we vnreuerently ſolemnize thoſe good memorials of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that to our vſe and to the glorie of God are, or may be well ordeined. As touching thoſe that haue left vs but ſome earthly bleſſing, yf we haue not them alſo in very thankfull reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>braunce; yf we deface their doinges, diminiſhe of their glorie, or raze their monume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts. As touching thoſe that are lately departed, yf we ſuffer them to lye vnburied; or burie them diſorderly; or impeach their good name; or neglect thoſe that they leaue behind them. As touching all inferior Creatures, yf inſolently we behaue our ſelues towardes them: or
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:19467:74"/> wantonly vſe them.</p>
                  <p>So we haue in this order to knit vnto<note n="*" place="margin">Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this knitting together to all, whereas notwithſtanding many of vs in euery Comm-wealth are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry yll and corrupt members, it may be doubted, howe we may knit vnto them, without ſome ſteine to our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, or breach of our duty. As tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching which it is to be knowne, firſt that it may very well ſtand together, that we vtterly miſlyke whatſoeuer is yll in them: and yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding euer carefully maineteine and vp-hold our mutuall or common ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietie with them. Then alſo, that there is none ſo yll, but that eyther alreadie there is ſome good thing in him, that may be commodious vnto vs, or, of him ſhall come ſome plant, that ſhall be of great price: or, yf nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of theſe be, yet for ought that we know, they may be: or els, though it were poſſible, that there were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge but naughtines in him, yet mighte he be a good patterne of the great goodnes of God towardes vs, that he hath not made vs ſuch as we take him to be. Which thinges ought to be of ſuch acompt with vs, as that in this caſe we ſhould euer kepe this moderation, ſo to keepe nerer to the better ſort, that yet we ſunder not our ſelues altogether from the worſt of all.</note> all: and to ſunder our ſelues fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this knitting together to all, whereas notwithſtanding many of vs in euery Comm-wealth are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry yll and corrupt members, it may be doubted, howe we may knit vnto them, without ſome ſteine to our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, or breach of our duty. As tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching which it is to be knowne, firſt that it may very well ſtand together, that we vtterly miſlyke whatſoeuer is yll in them: and yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding euer carefully maineteine and vp-hold our mutuall or common ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietie with them. Then alſo, that there is none ſo yll, but that eyther alreadie there is ſome good thing in him, that may be commodious vnto vs, or, of him ſhall come ſome plant, that ſhall be of great price: or, yf nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of theſe be, yet for ought that we know, they may be: or els, though it were poſſible, that there were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge but naughtines in him, yet mighte he be a good patterne of the great goodnes of God towardes vs, that he hath not made vs ſuch as we take him to be. Which thinges ought to be of ſuch acompt with vs, as that in this caſe we ſhould euer kepe this moderation, ſo to keepe nerer to the better ſort, that yet we ſunder not our ſelues altogether from the worſt of all.</note> none.</p>
                  <p>The promiſe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed therevnto, doth partely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecte particular perſons; but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, the whole people. As it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecteth particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, though the wordes ſeeme to promiſe longe life in this world without exceptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: yet are they ſo to be taken, as that they promiſe it in this worlde, as it ſhall be moſte ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient; in the worlde to come, without exception or limitation. and that the obſeruers therof, if they haue
<pb facs="tcp:19467:75"/> not the performance of this promiſe in this world (as in deede there is no time appointed) then, becauſe god is true, and iuſt, they are ſure to haue it in the world to come. For it is not euer ſene, that good ſubiectes are moſt cheriſhed: but ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes wrongfully, and vnnaturally cut off very ſone. howbeit their hope to haue this promiſe performed, is not therefore cut off therewithall: but much enlarged. So likewiſe on the other ſide it doth ſo threaten ſuch as breake it, to haue their dayes cut off, that neuertheleſſe they are in this worlde oftymes ouerſlipped: but then, ſo much the more ſure to be cut off from that longe, and bleſſed lyfe in the world to come. As it reſpecteth the whole people, it doth in like ſort not onely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe vnto them, that they ſhall peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly enioy their owne la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, ſo long as they ſhal thus linke together, by honouring eche other, as they ought to doe: but alſo threatneth, that they ſhall be rooted out thence, whenſoeuer they ſhall ſtart from thoſe bandes of vnitie, and ſunder, or diuide them ſelues from cache other. Whiche alſo came to paſſe among the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:19467:75"/> Iſraelites, after that the greateſt part of them, deuided them ſelues from the houſe of Dauid, to whome the Crowne was appointed of God. Out of which, all States haue in like ſorte to gather, that yf they ſhall in maner aforeſaid knit together, then ſhall they alſo long en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy their countrie, in peace, and proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: yf contrariwiſe they fall a ſunder, then doo they lay them ſelues open to the ſpoyle, and geue their lande occaſion to caſt them out, as vnnaturall, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerchargeable burdens for the earth to beare.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The ſixt Commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement.</head>
                  <p>BY the ſixte Commaundement are we taught, that vnto this kniting toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by honouring eche other, we alſo bring with vs a ſingular care of preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, to be ſpreade foorth vnto all, and to euery one. But whereas the three next Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes doe treate of diuers ſpeciall pointes of this care for eache other, that by this is requy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
<pb facs="tcp:19467:76"/> we may beſte take this to treate of it generally: leauing thoſe ſpecial points to the others. And ſo to proceede, we haue to conſider, that firſt it forbiddeth; then it requireth.</p>
                  <p>It forbiddeth, firſt the Braunche: then the Roote, and whatſoeuer other Braun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches come out of the ſame. The Braunch is murther. The Roote is, the neglecting of, or not caring for our neighbours good eſtate. The other Braunches that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede out of the ſame are very many. but yet ſuch, as that (deducting thoſe that doe properly apperteine to thoſe three Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes that nexte followe) all may be brought into a couple of princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall ſortes. Whereof the former is, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we annoy our neighbour in our Common Calling, or, as all menne ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally may doo. the other is, whereby we annoy him in our ſeuerall eſtates or trades of lyfe: behauing our ſelues ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, contrary to that which their nature re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth.</p>
                  <p>Of the former ſorte are theſe. Firſte, when wittingly, or of ſette purpoſe, we bende our ſelues againſte him or againſt
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:19467:76"/> his good eſtate, eyther in deede; or in word; or els but in thought. Secondarily when we are not ſo well aduiſed of our doinges, but that, althoughe we meane him no hurt, yet we are occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vnto him of ſtumbling in the way of his dutie: ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by word, as when we directly intice him to ſinne, or to ſome other inconueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; or but vtter ſuch thinges, as may inwardly corrupt him, or otherwiſe be ſome hurt vnto him: or by dede, when we walke ſo inordinately before him, that by our yll example, &amp; other doinges, we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolden him to ſome euill; or do him ſome hurt. Laſt of all whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we lead our lyues in ſuch ſorte, that they are not profitable vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our neighbours, as when we lyue in no honeſt labour at al: or els not ſo profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table as we might make them, as when we lyue in ſome ſuche trade as is not ſo needefull as others that we might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take our ſelues vnto: or hauing any good trade, doo not faythfully labour therein.</p>
                  <p>Of the other ſorte there be ſo many that that it is harde to reckon them vppe. but it ſhall be ſufficient to note a fewe prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall
<pb facs="tcp:19467:77"/> examples. Among Princes there are founde of theſe Braunches, when as eyther they ſuffer by their faulte vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers to take by violence their authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie from them: or fondly yeld it ouer to any forreine power: or put ſuche in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie vnder them, as are not meete for the place: or them ſelues be careleſſe in their charge not regarding either to haue any lawes; or, howe vicious, or weake they are; or, howe ſlenderly their good lawes be putte in execution, eyther by want of diligence therein, or by exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their prerogatiue to goe directly againſte the meaning of them. Among all inferior Magiſtrates (whether Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall, Ciuile, or Martiall) when they are eyther falſe, or negligent in their charge (ſo longe as they haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued in charge to doo no more then lawefully they may) as alſo on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide yf they pronounce ſentence, or doo execution accordinge as they are putte in truſte, or as the Lawes directe, ſo ofte as their charge, or the Lawes of the Realme are contrarie to the word of God. Among Spiritual Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:19467:77"/> or miniſters, when they haue ſo lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle care of their flocke, that eyther them ſelues are not reſident, or vſually a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them: or beeing there, deliuer vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them vnholſome doctrine: or, yf it be holſome, let them not haue it (other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe occupied, or louing their eaſe) plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully ynough: or be vtterly ſo voyde of all diſcretion or conſideration, that they put not their ſpirituall Cenſure in vre; both by their worde, and by their Sacramentes, to geue ſinners to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande in what caſe they are before God: or behaue them ſelues vnreuerently in their function: or lyue vngodlye: or without any ſufficient calling leaue their cure (for a greater lyuing) they care not to whome. Among Parentes, when they haue ſo little care of their Children, that they doo not ſufficiently to their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer relieue their bodily neceſſities: or pamper them ouermuch: or teach them not the knowledge or feare of God: or doe not invre them to labour in ſome godly trade, wherby they may be able to liue: or put them off fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds they care not how,
<pb facs="tcp:19467:78"/> for keeping, and furthering of them in the feare of God: or withholde them from mariage, when time is they ſhould marie: or force them to mary for their owne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite, or pleaſure, ſuch as they can not ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fancie. Among Scholemaſters or tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, when they corrupt thoſe children of God that are vnder their hands, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vnto them ſuch authors as may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect them eyther with Heatheniſh, or Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh religion; or bring to their knowlege any other ſuch naughtineſſe: or otherwiſe ſuffer them to decline to looſenes of lyfe: or put not ſo much vnto them in matters of good learning, as they are able to deale withall: or be ouer heauie &amp; greeuous vnto them. Among God-fathers and God-mothers, or thoſe that are ſureties for children when they are chriſtned, when as they doo ſo lightly paſſe ouer their charge to the parentes agayne: or do not very diligently endeuour them ſelues to teache them, firſt the principles of religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; then alſo the higher matters of greater perfection, ſo farre as is nedeful for them to knowe. Among maſters and dames, when they doo not diligently trayne vp
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:19467:78"/> their ſeruauntes in religion, and vertue: when they ſuffer them to be ydle: when they imploy them ill, or teache them ſome naughtines: when they ſet them aboute their owne bellies: or other worldly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayres on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sabboth day; eſpecially then, or at any time els, when of righte they ſhould be at Seruice, or Sermons: when they ſuffer them to outray in waſtfull ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, whether in apparell for their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters honor, or worſhippe; or howſoeuer els: or, when they occaſion them by their ſtraighte allowaunce, to ſeeke oute yll wayes to mainteine them ſelues. Among Artificers, when they lende foorth their hande, or their cunning to helpe forwarde ſinne; or, but to content the vanitie of men. Among the Richer ſorte, when as by their riches they do not endeuour them ſelues, to relieue the neceſſities of their neighbours about them: whether to the inſtruction of their ſoules, by preaching, and ſcholing: or to the reliefe of their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, with foode, apparell, harbour, phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke, ſurgery, &amp;c: or to their defence, and maynteinau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in their right, againſt thoſe that would beare them downe. Laſt of all
<pb facs="tcp:19467:79"/> (and to paſſe ouer many) among Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, when as they haue ſo little regarde to the Common-welth, that eyther they do without licence contrary thervnto: or els for their owne profite or pleaſure, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure licence to doo otherwiſe, then them ſelues doo ſee that it may beare.</p>
                  <p>It requireth firſt the Braunche: then al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the Roote, and whatſoeuer other brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches come out of the ſame. The Braunch is, to preſerue the lyfe of others. The Roote is a carefulnes for our neighbours good eſtate. The other Braunches are many and diuers: but of thoſe two ſorts before deſcribed. Firſte as touching our generall Calling, that whatſoeuer wee determine towardes him of ſet purpoſe, in deede, worde, or thought, it wholly tende to his preſeruation, and bettering. then that by our worde we doo both occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion him to goodnes, and alſo directly prouoke him thervnto: by our deede or outwarde behauiour &amp; conuerſation we do the like in both thoſe poyntes. Laſt of all, to the ende that our life may be moſte profitable vnto him, that we enter into that trade of life, wherby we may do moſt
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:19467:79"/> good; and faythfully occupie our ſelues therein. Then as touching euery ones ſpeciall degree or calling, that Princes keepe their kingdomes; and the gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of them in their owne handes: that they ſee that their lawes be good, tending to the ſame ende that Gods word preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth; and dooing it with the ſame equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie or moderation: that they be ſo care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to ſee them duly put in execution, as that neither them ſelues do vſe, or clayme any ſuch prerogatiue, as doth not helpe it forwarde; neither place ſuch vnder them (ſo nere as they can) as haue not that their full purpoſe; nor ſuffer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to continue in authoritie ſtil, that do degenerate. That al inferior magiſtrates do their dutie accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the charge co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted vnto them (ſo long as it varieth not from the worde of God, neither by nature, nor yet by circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance) truly, &amp; diligently: otherwiſe flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and playnly refuſe, eyther to geue ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence; or to do execution. That ſpirituall Paſtors be reſident where their charge is: breake vnto them the worde of God ſoundly, &amp; ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly: vſe their keyes to go together, whether it be to ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or to ſhut:
<pb facs="tcp:19467:80"/> keepe to the charge committed vnto them, vnleſſe God ſhall call them to ſome other. That Parents moderately relieue the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily neceſſities of their children: ſoundly inſtruct them in true religion: teache them vertuous &amp; godly behauiour: traine the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp in ſome trade, wherby they may do moſte good: put them not of fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their hands, but ſo as they ſee good likelyhood, of keping, and bettering the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the way of godlines: when they ſee it nedefull for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to marie, that they do both helpe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> forward; &amp; that where themſelues can beſt like in the feare of God. That Scholemaſters put by al ſuch Authors as may infect their ſcholers, eyther with Heatheniſh, or popiſh corrup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion: teach the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the principles of ſound re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: trayne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp in ciuile &amp; vertuous behauiour: and as for their maner of tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, firſt ſee that it be good; &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> folow it with diligence, and moderation. That Suerties for children at their chriſtening, do not paſſe ouer their charge to others: but the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues ſee that they be trayned vp as they ought, firſt in the principles; then in all other nedefull poyntes. That Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters &amp; Dames inſtruct their ſeruaunts in
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:19467:80"/> Religion: ſee that they beſtow not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both day, nor any ſuch other time lawfully exempted in worldly affayres; but in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine ſeruice, and ſuch other works, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſuch opportunities: kepe them euer ſufficiently occupied: teach them in al their doings faithfulnes &amp; truth: ſee that they ſpend not, but as they may beare it: and that they the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues allow the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo liberally, that both they may be able to maynteine their ſeruice; &amp; alſo haue ſome reaſonable co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuall encreaſe therby. That Artificers beſtow their labour and cunning in ſuche things only, as are to our nedeful &amp; ſober vſe. That the Richer ſort do their beſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuor to helpe their neighbours to inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for their ſoules; reliefe for their bodies; &amp; mainteinaunce in their right. Laſt of all that Subiects breake no good &amp; needefull lawes though they haue licence; nor pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure licence ſo to doo, in any matter that goeth agaynſt the Common-wealth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The ſeuenth Commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement.</head>
                  <p>THe ſeuenth Commaundement requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth ſo good regarde of euery one, as
<pb facs="tcp:19467:81"/> that we do in no wiſe annoy our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in his wedlocke; nor our ſelues walke ſo inordinatly in that kinde of vice, that it be eyther the ouerthrowing, or the daungering of any other. As touching which we haue in like ſort to conſider, firſt what it forbiddeth; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what it requireth.</p>
                  <p>It forbiddeth, firſt the Braunch: then the Roote, and whatſoeuer other Braunches come out of the ſame. The Braunche that here is ſpoken of, is Adulterie. The roote is an vnchaſt minde, or no ſounde care to keepe our ſelues chaſt. The other Braun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches that come out of the ſame, are diuers: but ſome more principall Braunches then others. Thoſe that are of the former ſort, are firſt and formoſt, all vnlawfull and vncleane copulations: ſecondarily, all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vncleane dedes that are of that kind: thirdly, vncleane talke: and laſt of al, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane thoughts. Of the other ſorte are theſe: ydlenes: companying with harlots, or light perſons: viewing of beautie: har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kening to wanton talke: deintie fare, or pampering of the body: any kinde of vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luptuous liuing: the vowe of ſingle life: not to marie when neede requireth: if we
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:19467:81"/> be maried, much to abſent our ſelues one from an other; or any way to ſuffer the loue and lyking that is betwixt vs to decay.</p>
                  <p>It requireth, firſt the Braunch: then al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the Roote, and whatſoeuer other Braunches come out of the ſame. The Braunche is to vp-holde and preſerue our neighbours chaſtitie, that they doo not commit adultrie. The other Braun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches are diuers: but as I ſayde before ſome more principall then others. Of the firſte ſorte are theſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we vtterly abhorre all ſuch copulation; and that all be chaſt and cleane, in dede; in word; &amp; in thought. Of the other ſort are theſe, to be occupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: to keepe companie with chaſte and cleane perſons: to turne a ſide our eyes from the beauty of others: to ſtoppe our eares to daungerous talke, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke it: to lyue an auſtere, and painfull life: to keepe our fredome in this point: to marie whenſoeuer nede requireth: yf we be maried, not to abſent our ſelues much but to kepe together: &amp; by al poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble meanes to mainteine our mutuall loue or liking one of an other.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19467:82"/>
                  <head>The eyght Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement.</head>
                  <p>THe eyght Commaundement doth in like ſort requier ſo vnfeyned a care of our neighbour, that we ſeeke not wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to gette from him any thing that is his. As touching which we haue in like ſort to conſider, firſt what it forbiddeth; then what it requireth.</p>
                  <p>It forbiddeth firſte the Braunch: then alſo the Roote, and whatſoeuer other Braunches come out of the ſame. The Braunch is to Steale. The Roote is to haue no care of our neighbours ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce, or vnrighteouſneſſe in getting of wealth; not to regarde howe we come by ſuch thinges, ſo long as any way we may get them. The other Braunches are diuers: but ſome more principall, then ſome others. Of the former ſort are thoſe wherby any wrong is done to our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in ſome part of his ſubſtaunce, or ſuch things as belong thervnto. Which wrong may be donne three manner of wayes. firſte by doing the deede it ſelfe. The deede it ſelfe may be iniurious two
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:19467:82"/> wayes. firſt yf it go directly againſte the worde of God, whether the lawes of our Princes goe therewithall (as in many kindes of our Extortion; Vſuries; De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceites; Defraudinges of heires, or ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors; and ſuch like): or whether it be but the lawe of God onely, going<note n="*" place="margin">As very many iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly paſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong vs. and namely the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maner of with-hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge the Church ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinges by right of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriation in the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of thoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are, eyther at al not oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupied in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miniſterie of the word or not in ſuch ſort as they ought ſo farre as they are able. Wherevnto alſo may be added (ſo far as I can ſee) almoſt all ſuch letting of Church lyuinges by leaſe, as is for a farther commoditie, then falleth with in the tyme of the leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor, and the procuring of things ſo to be let, or the enioying of the ſame: lykewiſe the making away, or diminiſhing by exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue ſpending, eyther landes or goodes, from thoſe to whome they ought to come, and ſuch lyke.</note> further, and to greater perfection, then oftymes the lawes of Princes regarde. Then if it go but againſte the lawes of Princes, in ſuch thinges as the worde of God hath it ſelfe left indifferent, but hath therewith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all left libertie vnto Magiſtrates to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine the ſame, as they fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tyme to time ſhall find expedient: as namely, to take to our ſelues any other allowaunce in apparell, fare, paſtime, price, hier, wages or ſuch lyke, then our lawes do allow vs to do. The ſecond kinde of wrong is, yf we do but conſent to others that do it; or
<pb facs="tcp:19467:83"/> conceale the ſame. The thirde, not to make reſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and recompence for ſuch iniuries as we haue done. Of the other ſort are, to liue an ydle &amp; an vnoccupied lyfe: to haue no ſufficient trade whereby we and ours may lyue: not to be content with our eſtate: prodigalitie, or ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous, and vaine expences.</p>
                  <p>It requireth, firſte the Braunch: then alſo the Roote, and whatſoeuer other Braunches grow out of the ſame. The Braunch is, to be true and iuſte, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that kinde of theft that commonly goeth vnder that name: or, ſo heartely to deteſt it, that we rather chuſe to die, then to ſuccour our ſelues by it. The Roote is, the loue of equitie in all ſuch caſes: or, when a man hath a care of his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours commoditie, in no wiſe to touch it, but to leaue it wholly vnto him ſelfe. The other Braunches that doo proceede of the ſame Roote, are alſo diuers: but ſome more principall, then others. The former ſort may be thus contracted. Firſt our ſelues to take hede, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we medle with nothing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is not our own. As for others, if any woulde proloine away his goods
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:19467:83"/> or by open violence ouerlay him for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, not to ſuffer any ſuch ſo neere as we can: yf any haue already done it that we know of, to helpe him to his right againe to the vttermoſte of our power. Yf in tymes paſte we haue done him wrong, whether warranted by the lawes of our countrie, or not, firſte to make to him, or his a full reſtitution: then alſo to make to him or his a ſufficient recompence for his want thereof, ſo farre (at the leaſt) as we are able. The latter ſorte are, euer to be occupied in ſome godly labour: our ſelues to haue ſuch a trade (ſo nere as we can) as is ſufficient maintenaunce for vs, not iniuring any: to be faythfully occupied therin: and to be very ſpare and moderate in all our owne priuate expences.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The nynth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement.</head>
                  <p>THe nynth Commaundement in lyke ſort requireth ſo good aduiſment on his behalfe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we euer ſeke to vphold our ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ghbours good name. But as touching this alſo, we haue to conſider, firſte what it forbiddeth; then what requireth.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19467:84"/>
                  <p>It forbiddeth, firſte the Braunch: then alſo the Roote, and whatſoeuer other Braunches come out of the ſame. The Braunch is, the bearing of falſe witnes againſt our neighbour. The roote is whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath no ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d care of his neighbours good name or eſtimatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The other Brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ches y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> come out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame are, to be inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitiue (being but priuat me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or doing it but to feede our humors) of our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours faultes: to miniſter occaſion to talke of the ſame: to diſcloſe them to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to his ſhame: to ſpeake the truth of him, to reproche him withall: to reuile, mocke, or taunt him, with open rebukes, plaine ſcoffes, or ſecret quippes; ſo to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſe or diſcredite him, or but to make o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers mery: to beare with others that ſo do, and not to ſhewe forth a miſliking of it: and ouer lightly to paſſe ouer our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, not conſidering that we haue ben, or may be as bad as the worſt.</p>
                  <p>It requireth, firſte the Braunch: then alſo the Roote, and whatſoeuer other Braunches come out of the ſame. The Braunche is ſo to abhorre falſe witnes, that on the other ſide we be readie to ſay the whole truth on our neighbours
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:19467:84"/> behalfe. The Roote is, to be ſtudious to vpholde a good report of our neighbour ſo farre as we may conueniently. The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Braunches are, to be readie to couer his nakednes, and faultes: gladly to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge ſuch vertues, and other good qualities as he hath, how yll ſoeuer he be otherwayes: redely to geue him, as occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſhall ſerue, his iuſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendation: yf at any tyme we be diſpoſed in the way of honeſt mirth to ſpeake pleaſantly of him, to be ſure that it tend to no yll: yf we be in place where he is reproched, to defend him ſo well as we may; and to turne the talke eyther altogether from him, or ſo much as we may to his commendation: and laſt of all to caſt our eyes vppon our ſelues, and our owne doings, that ſo fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, that we would be loth to haue our owne faultes written in our fore-heads, we may be the more deſirous to couer our neighbours.<note n="*" place="bottom">Herewithall it is good to conſider, that as this vice before deſcribed doth become all men very yll, but much more thoſe that are of ſome accompt, as the learned, aged, honourable, or ſuche lyke, and moſt of all thoſe that ſit in place of iudgement, eſpecially when they are on their iudgement ſeates: ſo on the other ſide the contrary vertue doth become all menne well, at all times &amp; in al places, but much more thoſe that are in bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter accompt, then the reſt, and moſt of all Iudges to whome is committed the ſentence of equitie, to be pronounced by their mouthes, eſpecially when they are in place of iudgement. that ſo the reuerence of their perſons, the excellencie of their office, and the maieſtie of their iudgement ſeates may the leſſe be ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhed, and ſhine more clerely.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19467:85"/>
                  <head>The tenth Commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement.</head>
                  <p>THe laſte, or tenth Commaundement chargeth euery one to be content with his eſtate: and ſo conſequently requy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth ſo notable a moderation to be grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in vs, as may very well, both helpe forwarde our Common Societie; and alſo prepare a man the better to walke the harde and painefull way of theſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes. But as touching it, we haue alſo to conſider, firſt what it forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth; then what it requireth.</p>
                  <p>It forbiddeth, firſte the Braunch: then alſo the Roote, and whatſoeuer other Braunches come out of the ſame. The Braunche that firſte he ſpeaketh of, is to couet.<note n="*" place="margin">As tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching this coueting it is to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that he ſpeketh not of coueting anye thing wrongfully or to haue any of thoſe thynges while the right of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> appertey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to our neighbour (for ſo ſhuld it be confou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded wyth the eight, &amp; parſly with the ſeuenth commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement: but of coueting or wiſhing rightfully to haue, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bettering of our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what that as yet ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perteineth to our nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour.</note> the example is geuen of our neighbours houſe more ſpecially are forbiddden diuers members: as to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uet
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:19467:85"/> his wife, his man-ſeruaunt, his maid-ſeruaunt, his Oxe, his Aſſe, or any thing els. The Roote is the miſliking, or not an heartie liking of the eſtate that it hath pleaſed God to caſte vppon vs: and yet no further, but that we couet no better, vnleſſe by lawefull meanes (as we call them) we might come there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto. Of the other Braunches that come our of the ſame there be two ſortes. In time of aduerſitie when the Croſſe is layde vppon vs, or when thinges fall not out as we woulde haue them, to be ſo diſquieted in mynde, that fyrſt we cleane forget the hope that we haue of a better eſtate in the worlde to come; or els forſake the holde of it, or (at leaſte) a good parte thereof. then com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming downe to our ſelues, in our im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paciencie eyther deſtroy our ſelues: or furiouſly doo our ſelues, or others ſome hurte: or open our mouthes to blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie and curſing: or languiſhe away in the greefe of our mynde: or in ſecrete mutter, or murmure at it: or ſeeke to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent it, or get it away by inordinate mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes (as by wiſhing, or ſeeking out hidden
<pb facs="tcp:19467:86"/> treaſure in the ſea or lande: or any ſuche like.) In time of Proſperitie, or when thinges fall out as we would haue them, to be ſo puft vp with inordinate ioy, that firſt, we eyther cleane forget; or make lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle accompt of that whiche hereafter is to come, the very ſubſtaunce of our hope. Then comming downe to oure earthly Paradiſe, eyther wholly ſet our hartes on it: or by meanes therof become very wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons (forgetting our ſelues in manye pointes of our duties): or laye ſo faſte hold of it, that we declare our ſelues ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, that we ſhould be very lothe to parte with it agayne, whenſoeuer it ſhoulde pleaſe God to take it away.</p>
                  <p>It requireth, firſt the contrarie Braun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che: then alſo the Roote, and whatſoeuer other Braunches come out of the ſame. The Braunches is, in all our ſecrete and in moſt thoughts, to leaue vnto all men, whatſoeuer preſently is theirs, to them and theirs for euer. The Roote is a ſound and an hartie lyking of whatſoeuer eſtate it pleaſeth God at any time to caſte vpon vs: not ſo much as once in hart wiſhing to haue it bettered any one iote.</p>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:19467:86"/>
                  <p>Of the other Braunches that come out of the ſame, there are likewiſe two ſortes. In time of aduerſitie, or when the Croſſe is layde vpon vs, or when things fal out otherwiſe then we would haue wiſhed, to be of ſo quiet, ſo pacient, &amp; ſetled mindes, that we firſt caſte vp our eyes vnto the bleſſed eſtate, that is prepared for thoſe that ſuffer for righteouſnes ſake heere; and euer keepe a faſt holde thereof. then comming downe to our burden here, that we quietly beare it, ſo long as it pleaſeth god it ſhal be our portion: hartely thanke him for it alſo, as well as for better: ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther chooſe to beare it, then to be without it (ſo long as ſo it pleaſeth God) though otherwiſe it were left to our own choyce. In time of proſperitie, or when we are in ſuche a caſe as dothe very well pleaſe vs, to be of that ſtay and moderation ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall, that firſt we accompt it nothing, in compariſon of that other that is layde vp for vs agaynſt the worlde to come: and that euer we endeuour our ſelues to looke through it, vnto the other, that it take not from vs the ſighte thereof. Then as touching the thing it ſelfe, that we
<pb facs="tcp:19467:87"/> neither take occaſion thereby to ſlippe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide from our moderation, to ſome poynt of vanitie: nor in hart cleaue ſo faſt ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto, but that we can be content to parte with it agayne with right good will, if it pleaſe God to take it from vs.</p>
                  <p>Could this Commaundement be well kept of vs, neither ſhoulde we ſo muche ſtreine our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ſocietie: neither ſhould we thinke it ſo harde and ſo painefull a matter, to indure the way of Gods Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Concluſion of the whole: of th'ende and vſe of this Lawe.</head>
               <p>By all theſe conſidered together it may ſufficiently appeare, that ſeeing thys moſte holy Lawe requireth ſo abſolute perfection (an other manner of thinge then mortall men are able to come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to any thing neere, ſynce that they fell) and hath a moſte fearefull curſe, or ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of eternall damnation to thoſe that ſhall breake any iote thereof (excepting none others, but thoſe that ſeeke the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhmente
<pb facs="tcp:19467:87"/> thereof on their behalfe in Ieſus Chriſte) therefore is this Lawe geuen, to thoſe that are Ignoraunte of their abilitie, or eſtate, to teache them that this way, that is, by the righteouſneſſe of workes, there is no ſaluation to be had, for that they are not able to performe the ſame. ſo to driue them all to the other, to ſeeke their iuſtification by Fayth: that is, by the death and merites of Ieſus Chriſt. To thoſe that do come vnto Chriſt, to giue them to vnderſtande, from how great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibilitie he hath deliuered them, who hath performed the ſame to their vſe: how fully he hath anſwered the iuſtice of God, in that he hath wrought for vs ſo perfect righteouſnes; and ſo conſequently howe ſubſtancially he hath wrought our ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: and what is the way, or what are the workes, wherein we ſhoulde walke and beſtowe our labour; and that, not vnprofitably, although we be not able to walke in ſuche ſorte as it requireth. To thoſe that will not ſo take holde of Chriſt, but that they will needes be ſaued, eyther in the whole, or in ſome parte, by their owne halfe-faced workes, or by ſome
<pb facs="tcp:19467:88"/> other waye beſides, or els not at all, to teach them, that as for their beſt endeuour (when they haue done but what they can, and not all, or euery iote) neither it, nor any other helpe will be able to ſerue their purpoſe in this matter: but that eyther they muſt doo all, and euery iote, euen the vttermoſte farthing that is due by theſe Commaundementes, or els be damned without redemption. For that it hath not pleaſed God (as alſo it coulde not ſtande with his Iuſtice) to ſaue by their beſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour, or any way els: but by taking holde of, or putting their truſt, onely, and ſoundly in Ieſus Chriſte. That ſo they may knowe, that becauſe they doo not vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly renounce their owne works, and whatſoeuer els; nor can abide to be ſaued, onely by their Fayth in Chriſt: therfore doo they worthely periſhe.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="quotation">
            <pb facs="tcp:19467:88"/>
            <head>Deut. 4. a. 5-9.</head>
            <p>Beholde, I haue taught you ordinances and lawes, ſuch as the Lord my god com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded me, that ye should do ſo in the lande vvhither ye goe to poſſeſſe it. Kepe them therfore, and do them. For that is your wiſdome and vnderſtanding in the ſight of other nations: that they maye heare all theſe ordinances, and ſay; Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it is a wiſe and vnderſtanding people: it is a great nation. For vvhat other na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is ſo great, that haue their gods come ſo nigh vnto them, as the Lord our God is nigh vnto vs in all things, as oft as vve call vnto him? Yea and what nation is ſo great, that hath ordinances and lawes ſo righteous, as all this lawe vvhiche I ſet before you this day? Take hede to thee ſelfe therefore, and keepe thy ſoule dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently, that thou forget not the things that thine eyes haue ſeene, and that they depart not out of thine heart all the dayes of thy life: but teache them thy ſonnes, and thy ſonnes ſonnes.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
